Good evening everyone. It's 6:30 and I'm
going to call to order this May 13, 2025
meeting of Lancaster City Council.
Welcome everyone to Council Chambers. A
few reminders at the top of the meeting.
This meeting and its participants are
being recorded. Please take a moment to
silence your phones and devices if you
haven't done so already. During this
evening's meeting, there will be several
opportunities for public comment. The
first public comment period is for
residents that registered in advance to
speak about items not on the agenda.
Residents may also comment on individual
legislative items. Finally, a second
public comment period will be at the end
of the agenda agenda for any other
speakers wishing to address council. All
speakers should begin with their name
and block of residence for our meeting
record and address their comments toward
council. All comments are limited to
three minutes per speaker. To keep time,
this light will turn green when a
speaker begins. It will blink yellow
when there's one minute remaining and it
will turn red when three minutes has
been expended. Thank you in advance for
ensuring that time is kept equally for
all. speakers addressing council and the
members of the audience will be expected
to conduct themselves in an orderly
manner and remain respectful of others.
Thank you in advance for that as well.
And now for all of those who are willing
and able, please rise for the pledge of
allegiance to the
flag of the
stands
for Mr. Mr. Harris, would you please
call the role of members? Yes, Madam
President. Mr. Med here. Mr. Roya here.
Mr. Cle here. M. Craig here. Miss Diaz
here. Mr. Hirs here. President B here.
I'll also just make one more note
because we are working um with a
temporary audio system. I'll ask
everyone on the deis and anyone speaking
from the podium to please make sure that
you're speaking very directly into the
microphone. Thank you. Uh, our first
item is the approval of the minutes of
the April 29th, 2025 meeting of council.
Motion to approve. Second. We have a
motion and a second. Any council
comments on the minutes?
Hearing none. Mr. Harris. Mr. Med. I.
Mr. Royal. I. Mr. Cle. I. Mr. Craig. I.
Miss Diaz. I. Mr. Hersh. I. President.
I. We'll now move into proclamations,
honors, awards, and resolutions of
recognition. Our first item is
recognizing the accreditation of
Lancaster Bureau of Police. Um, I'll
turn that over to I see Chief Mendes
here or Mayor Srachi, whoever would like
to begin.
Chief, welcome. And just make sure that
that uh light is on. I believe it's a a
red light or a green light. It's red.
It's red. That sounds good. Okay. All
right. Well, thanks for having us. Um,
this has been a long time to get here as
you all are aware. Um, so appreciate
the, you know, sticking with us as we
went through this. Uh, appreciate the
mayor for all her support as well. Uh,
we have Jim Adams from the Pennsylvania
Chiefs of Police Association here. We'll
have him come up. He'll do, uh, some
speaking and then we'll make the
official uh, uh, presentation of the
accreditation. Thank you.
Thank you, Chief Mendes, and thank you,
uh, city council for giving me this
opportunity to publicly recognize all
the hard work that your police
department put into this and what this
certificate means. It's more than just a
certificate that's going to be hanging
in the lobby. A lot of hard work went
into this. We're I'm not sure when
Lancaster City Police Department
actually started working on it, but I
can tell you when it really kicked off
is when your mayor sent a letter, which
I happen to bring a copy along uh back
in December of uh 2021. Uh because we
first of all to enroll in our program,
we need two endorsements, one from the
police chief and one from somebody
representing the municipality, which in
this case is your mayor. So, she sent a
letter representing the city. A short
time later, your chief uh Mendes uh came
on board and really got the process
going. Uh Lieutenant Reich is your
accredititation manager. Uh really
worked hard on it. What this certificate
represents is 125 best practices in
providing law professional law
enforcement services. And the process
real quickly, and I know I'm limited on
time, is for them to take a look at the
the 125 best practices, we call them
standards, and make sure that they have
policy written directives or uh whatever
they they call their their manual that
addresses each one of those. And when I
say 125 best practices, it's sort of bit
a little bit of a misnomer because when
you look at each of those standards,
there's a lot of what we call bullets or
individual standards embedded in that
that they also have to have written
directives for. When you add them all
up, that's 370 best practices that this
certificate
represents. This is not a certificate
for life. Uh our program first rolled
out in 2001. Uh since then we've
accredited 220 police departments in the
Commonwealth of Pennsylvania. We
currently have 189 accredited agencies.
We lose about one every year. Your
police department now is included in
that 189 uh police
departments. You take a look at what are
some of the benefits of this. First of
all, the insurance industry recognizes
that by being accredited is one of the
key risk management situations that you
can you can uh do and they actually some
insurance companies that write your
liability policies actually give a
discount because the studies show when
you compare similar police departments
not just in Pennsylvania but across this
nation, accredited police departments
get sued significantly less often than
nonacredited police departments. And
when accredited police departments do
get sued, the payouts are significantly
less. So by virtue of your police
department becoming accredited, you're
saving your insurance company money.
That's just one small benefit. Another
benefit, I know it's a little dated, but
after the George Floyd incident, some of
our state legislators came out with the
eight can't wait law enforcement
initiatives. Eight policies that they
felt can't wait. They need to be um
instituted immediately in police
departments. We agreed. We agreed so
much that accredited police departments
already had those eight can't wait
initiatives already addressed by policy.
So we try to stay ahead of what's going
on a little bit, not all the time. We're
constantly every year come out with an
updated standards manual. Uh we just
rolled out uh April the 1 of every year
we roll out our new standards manual.
It's now up to 130 best practices
because of things that are going on.
Another area as far as um uh benefits,
the statistics show not only do lawsuits
go down, but job related injuries go
down. Uh vehicle crashes involving
police cars go down. There's a whole
list of of benefits uh as far as being
accredited. Now that they're accredited,
we sent a team of three assessors in to
review their policies. And it's not just
about having solid policies in place.
You can have the best policy manual in
the world, but if nobody's following
those policies, it really doesn't do you
much good. So part of our process is for
every one of those 370 best practices,
they had to provide a minimum of two
what we call proofs of compliance,
proofs that their staff is actually
following those 370 best practices.
Three years from now, we'll be sending
in a fresh team of new assessors and
they'll be going through the entire
process again. On an annual basis, your
accredititation manager has to do what
we call an annual report where he
basically does a self assessment of your
agency and puts themselves through their
own assessment on an annual basis. It's
constant improvement. It's constantly
updating their policies, making sure
that they're in the forefront of best
practices. I can stand up here and talk
all night long about accreditation and
best practices, but I'm not going to do
that. But seriously, anybody in this
room uh can log on to the PA chief's uh
website. Just Google
phe.org. Um a web page will come up.
There's an accredititation tab. There's
a lot of information uh about our
program, about accreditation. Those 125
standards, 370 best practices are all
listed there. Feel free to look at them.
If you have any questions, my contact
information there. I contact I provided
a business card with your mayor. She can
share it with everybody. But seriously,
before you ask any questions, take a
look at the website and you have a
resident expert now in house because
they've been through the process.
They've been working on it for 5 years.
They got there. It's not important as
far as how long it takes. What's
important is you now have an accredited
police department. Thank you very much
for your time. I'd like to now publicly
call up your chief and present the
certificate. Also, mayor, you were
instrumental and certainly if you'd like
to come down too, I'd like to present
this publicly recognizing the Lancaster
Bureau of Police as an accredited law
enforcement agency.
[Applause]
Council President, if I may. Yes. I uh I
just want to uh thank uh Chief Mendes uh
for your leadership in bringing this to
fruition. This was a a task that um was
uh high on my list um from very early on
during my tenure. I I want to also
acknowledge Lieutenant Reich. Um I'm
gonna ask you to stand up,
sir. Thank you. Um Lieutenant Reich uh
uh was responsible for gathering all of
the proofs to demonstrate that we were
following those best practices and will
continue to be responsible for the
accreditation. Um anyone who wants to
read our police policies, they are
available on our website. Uh, and you
can crosswalk them obviously with the
Pennsylvania um, police chiefs
association. And um, this I just want
council and the public to be aware uh,
and underscore something that Mr. Adams
said, which is that this is an ongoing
process. This is not a onceanddone. It
does require ongoing reertification
um, and accreditation. And we do that by
demonstrating that we are maintaining
our policies uh up to date. Those of you
who were with me in 2018 knew that our
use of force policy needed to be
updated. We began that process, but now
I can say that all of our policies are
updated with best practices. And Chief
Mendes um is here tonight um uh
to demonstrate the commitment of the
bureau of upholding those best
practices. And so we really appreciate
your leadership. Um to those members of
the bureau that are here in the room
tonight, thank you for your service to
our city. Um we appreciate you and um
and are grateful for the work that's
been put in uh to continue the the
journey of of uh maintaining uh the best
that we can be not only in Lancaster
County but across Pennsylvania. Thank
you. All right. Thank you. Again, thanks
everybody. If I could just recognize a
few people here today. Um, first I
appreciate the kind words, but uh the
reality is it's the men and women of the
department that consistently provide
this service and they have um and
they're constantly looking to get better
and training and making sure they're
doing the best they can. So um if I
could first have if you're from the
Lanster City Police Department, please
stand up. Um this belongs to you.
And then lastly, if I could just thank
uh Lieutenant Pasentino from Manheim
Township Police Department and Chief
Jared Han from Littis for showing your
support today. I'd like to recognize
them as well. Thank you very much,
Chief, and uh my sincere appreciation
for uh all of the department for going
through this process and their
commitment and understanding the
importance of it. Thank you. Thank you.
[Applause]
As we proceed through the agenda,
particularly in the beginning here
during our proclamations and honor
section, uh just wanted to mention I
know that there are some people who may
be here for just one particular item.
And while you're always welcome to stay
for our entire council meeting, it's
also okay if you need to step out. So,
um I'll take a brief pause in case that
applies to anyone. and I'll do the same
after each of these uh resolutions of
recognition come up. Um and then we'll
proceed. So, thank you.
Right. Uh our next resolution of
recognition is council resolution number
32 2025. Mr. Harris, if you would. Yes,
madam president.
A resolution of the council of the city
of Lancaster designating July 27th to
July 29, 2025 as Lafayette days in the
city of Lancaster in recognition of the
bicesentennial of the great patriots
visit to our city.
Motion to approve. Second. Have a motion
and a second. Thank you counselors. uh
Lafayette Days is being recognized to uh
to honor the bicesentennial of
Lafayette's visit AC well historical
tour across the country and specifically
visit to Lancaster. This evening Ben
Weber is here who has a brief
presentation about Lafayette days in
Lancaster. Good evening. Good evening.
Thank you so much uh to the entire city
council. Uh this is a great honor for
our committee to be able to explain uh
something of our bicesentennial
celebration. Uh we entitle it uh
Lafayette in Lancaster, but we too have
a website uh Lafayette
200pa.org. Uh so there's many events
that I'll be uh uh touching on that you
can uh sign up for. But Lafayette and
Lancaster, if we can move on to the next
one. Uh essentially in July of this
year, uh we will be participating as
part of a 13-month reenactment of
Lafayette's farewell tour. Uh and this
is a a host of festivities that are
being planned all throughout the the 24
states that he visited. These are both
online as well as in-person educational
presentations that are being offered to
the public free of charge uh for the
most part uh but all in advance of uh
Ben Goldman who is the reenactor the
Lafayette reenactor uh there. Uh so next
slide please. Uh the basic question all
comes back to who is Lafayette? And some
of our younger folks in the audience may
have no clue. In fact, some folks who
are under 40 years old may have no clue
who Lafayette was because somehow or
other we stopped teaching about who
Lafayette was in public schools here in
the United States. Uh and uh so in a
brief brief primer, Lafayette at the age
of 19 was an extraordinarily wealthy
French aristocrat who heard about the
American Revolution and its ideals of
equality, liberty, and uh uh justice for
everyone. And he said, "I want to be a
part of that." Now, he was fabulously
wealthy. So he bought his own ship, came
over to join the Revolutionary War army,
probably doled out a whole lot of other
uh money, and essentially bought himself
a major general ship in the
Revolutionary War uh army. He helped to
supply the uh uh troops at Valley Forge.
Uh he became a fast friend of of George
Washington, wounded at the battle of
Brandy Wine, assisted the revolutionary
war uh the revolutionary army in many of
their maneuvers. Uh ended up being able
to convince the French Navy to become
involved. They trapped Cornwallis at
Yorktown from the sea. uh and uh
Lafayette led the troops trapping
Cornwallis uh uh at Yorktown from the
land. Essentially, we would not be a
nation without Lafayette. He's an
incredibly incredibly important person
and yet is so often forgotten. Next
slide, please.
uh to show off his celebrity in the
1800s when the capitol was built. That's
the a picture of the US House of
Representatives chamber. That's where
the uh uh state of the union is given
every year. And you'll see on the left
hand side there's a larger than-l life
fulllength portrait of George
Washington. That's Lafayette on the
right hand side. Lafayette and
Washington or were of similar celebrity
as they moved forward uh uh and the
birth of the of the union. Uh next slide
please. Now the farewell tour uh took
place uh but at the uh insistence of
James Monroe the uh president in 1824.
He was going through some times of I
don't know civil turmoil and political
difficulties something that we as a
democracy are faced day in day out at a
nationwide level as well as here in
every municipality. But uh they wanted
to reinstill the spirit of 1776 in the
populace and they invited the only
living revolutionary war general to come
back from France 50 years later and to
tour the uh the United States. Next
slide
please. Uh he ended he was to come for
just three months. He ended up staying
13 visiting battlefields cities, old
friends, prominent citizens. He traveled
to each of the 24 existing American
states at the time, covering 6,000
miles, not by car and not by plane, not
by train. That was horse and carriage uh
or boat. Uh and after 13 months, he was
returned home uh by John Quincy Adams,
who was the president in 1825. Next
slide, please.
Now, Lafayette was invited to Lancaster
by your predecessors, and I'm addressing
the city council. The city council in
1824 wanted Lafayette to come to uh come
to the city, invited him, and
unfortunately he wasn't able to make it
here until July of 1825. We have a
letter from him expressing his apologies
to you uh uh from back in uh in
1825. And uh when he finally made it
here in July, uh the the uh city and the
count the county uh had only a scarce
two weeks to prepare for his visit. And
it's amazing all what happened. He uh
arrives on the Philadelphia Langster
turnpike, what we call route 30 today uh
and arrives on uh with three Barouch
carriages uh in Gap at uh 10:30 in the
morning. Next, please. He stops in
Paradise uh and reviews a military
gathering at what was called Groves
Field at 3:40 in the afternoon. That
area is known today as Lafayette Tower
Park. Go figure. So people did remember
that Lafayette came through Lancaster.
Next,
please. He enters the city at 5:30 in
the afternoon and parades through until
7:00. Next,
please. The question I love to ask is,
what did Lafayette see that we can still
see today? Next, please.
as he comes into Lancaster, the first
thing that still stands, it's not that
big prison that wasn't built for another
few decades. It was that marker from the
Philadelphia to Lancaster turnpike
that's still standing today. And that's
one of the first things that Lafayette
would have seen once he crossed the city
uh boundary, please. Next slide. Then he
made this massive parade all throughout
uh the city of Lancaster going I'm sorry
west on King Street. Can you imagine
west? He travels west on King Street.
Now the city council had adopted an
ordinance requiring all residents, all
city citizens to clear the streets of
all the detritus, all the animals, all
the wagons so that this uh parade could
pass. All those streets were well known.
uh and uh uh um were well identified and
uh were cleared. I'm not sure if anyone
got arrested, but uh they uh the parade
took place. Uh four enormous uh flowered
arches were placed on each of the main
uh streets heading into the center
square. Um, and uh, thankfully Lancaster
City has uh, uh, really worked hard to
preserve a lot of the historic
structures that uh, tell us the
character of our community over the
years that that show off the charm uh,
of the city and its legacy, its
heritage. uh your uh historic
preservation specialist Suzanne
Stallings was very kind to identify
along that parade route what structures
would have stood in place uh back then
or that are still with us today and it's
34 there are 34 structures that
Lafayette would have seen that are still
in place today. Working with Historic
Preservation Trust we intend to mark
each of those. So you might see some
lawn signs coming popping up from time
to time between now and July. Next
slide,
please. So as he moves through, he also
uh back on July uh 27 of 1825, he
attends a a ball at the Masonic Hall and
spends the night at Slaymakers
Pennsylvania Arms Hotel on East King
Street, which is where today the Blazing
Jay's uh hot chicken hot sandwiches is.
Right. That's where the That's where
Lafayette spent the nights that he was
here was at the Pennsylvania Arms Hotel.
Next slide,
please. Now, this is an image of the
Masonic Hall uh with the Grace Building
in the background. You'll see the old
city hall is just to the right of that.
Uh and if you were to uh go to that,
that's where uh uh Fox, Duck, Passenger
Coffee, a couple of uh other places are
in that building. Above is this
marvelous uh uh uh area where the
banquet took place. Next, please. Uh
this is the Masonic Hall and this
gorgeous ceiling. Next slide, please. Uh
and then two incredible uh uh pieces of
art at either end. This is where the
ball took place that you had to be
invited to. Next slide, please. And we
do have uh as kept by Langster history a
copy of that golden ticket. Uh wouldn't
got gotten you to Willy Wonka's
chocolate factory would have gotten you
to this ball. Next slide
please. So as uh Lafayette moves through
the next day uh that was just one day he
attends festivities at the Lancasterian
school which is where the uh old post
office building is along Chestnut
Street. Next please. and he meets with
local clergy there after meeting with
students. Next, please. Uh he visits
with quite a few uh prominent local
citizens. Next, please. Uh and then he
celebrated at a feast in the courthouse.
Now, this feast was paid for again by
you, by city council. Uh you hosted uh
the Marque de Lafayette to a fabulous
feast at the courthouse. Now, this might
not be the courthouse that many of you
recall. This courthouse actually was in
a different location. If you could
please the next
slide. The courthouse at the time was in
the middle of what we call Penn square
where a soldiers and sailors monument is
today. Uh this is where the county
courthouse stood for many many years. Uh
this is an 1802 illustration uh of the
courthouse then. Again, this is where
soldiers and sailors monument is in the
middle of Penn Square as uh depicted in
1802 where you hosted a massive banquet
uh in Lafayette's honor. Uh after uh
Lafayette returned to uh France and then
died about a decade later though it took
about a month for word to be received by
again your predecessor city council in
1834. And upon hearing of the news of
Lafayette's death, uh each of your
predecessors took an uh a promise to
wear a black crepe around your your uh
arm uh to drape the council chambers for
a period of six months and to muffle all
the church bells in town again for six
months uh in mourning of the death of
this incredibly great man. Next slide,
please.
Here's uh a hundred years later. You can
see uh the soldiers and sailors
monument. This is before Grace building.
There's the central market. Our life
moves on. Uh it continues to thrive.
Next slide,
please. Now, we have a number of things
people can get uh uh excited to uh be a
part of. Again, more information at
lafayette uh
200pa.org. Uh there's an exhibit at
Historic Rock Ford. Several uh walking
tours. Uh we've got a virtual series of
uh Lafayette speakers. Next slide,
please. Uh again, at Lafayette Tower
Park, there's going to be a large
ceremony uh where 5,000 people gathered
in in uh 1825. That was 10% of the
entire population of the county got
together. Hopefully, we don't get that
many people this time. We just can't uh
handle that. But then there's a a
presentation at uh Franklin Marshall
College. We'll be having a a candlelight
dinner and period ball at the Trust 46
building. Next slide,
please. a Lafayette day at Historic Rock
Ford where you'll be able to see a
replica of one of those flowered arches
that spann across the city streets.
There'll be a summer uh evening with a
musical performance at the war center
and a closing ceremony and send off uh
down in Drewore State. Next slide,
please. So, thank you so much for your
attention this evening and for uh all
the supporting organizations. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Weber. Thank
you very
much. We have a little official business
after our history lesson. Uh we have a
motion and a second. Are there any uh
comments from council on the resolution
from the public?
Hearing none. Mr. Harris, Mr. Med I. Mr.
Roya. I Mr. Cle I. M Craig. I Miss Diaz.
Hi, Mr. Hirs. I President Baker I thank
you. Uh Mr. Weber, I have a presentation
copy of the resolution for you to take
back to your organizations. Um and we
can just pause for a brief photo if
you'd like. Very much so. Indulge me for
one moment. Thank you.
Thank you so much. Uh, our next item
under this part of the agenda is
resolution number 33 2025. Mr. Harris,
if you would.
Yes, m president. A resolution of the
city council in the city of Lancaster
recognizing May 2025 as bike month in
the city of Lancaster.
Motion to approve. Second. We have a
motion and a second. Council Hirs. Thank
you, Council President. Um, resolution
33 recognizes May is National Bike
Month. Um, and I'd like to invite Laura
Pauls Thomas and Leia Zikna from uh,
Global Shapers to give a brief
presentation on some of the exciting
things that are happening this bike
month here in Lancaster.
Good evening. Thank you for being here.
Thanks for having
us. You can go to the next
slide. Good evening everyone. Thank you
for allowing us the opportunity to speak
about global shapers and our ride roll
and stroll initiative. My name is Leah
Zikmund. I am the incoming curator for
our 24 25 year of our Lancaster hub. And
I'm joined tonight by Laura Pauls Thomas
who is our ride roll and stroll project
lead. The Global Shapers community is a
network of young people working together
to address local, regional, and global
challenges. We are one of over 500 hubs
in 152 countries. Lancaster is one of 16
in the northeastern United States alone
and are part of nearly 20,000 Shapers
and Shaper alumni. Global Shapers
self-organize into hubs like our
Lancaster Hub to develop and partner on
projects that address the specific and
wide ranging needs of our community. Our
global connectivity allows us to share
ideas, collaborate for a broader impact,
and engage a variety of perspectives as
we work towards change in our
community. The Global Shapers Lancaster
Hub was established in 2015 and is one
of three hubs in Pennsylvania alongside
Philadelphia and Pittsburgh. Our hub
maintains an average of about 20 members
and we are proud to have connections to
over 35 Lancaster Schaffer alumni.
Switch slide, please.
And you can actually advance to the next
one. Sorry about
that. As you can see, our hub
connections are intentionally diverse
across industry, interest, background,
and more in an effort to best represent
our Lancaster community. Next slide,
please. Over the years, projects have
addressed housing equity,
sustainability, and environmentalism,
tech literacy for refugees, and youth
innovation. This year, our projects are
focused on workforce development. rain
garden rewing and active transportation.
I'm excited to turn it over to Laura to
talk further about involvement with
active transportation in
Lancaster. Thanks, Leah. Thank you,
counselors. Thank you, Mayor Sarra. My
name is Laura Pauls Thomas. I'm a global
shaper and the founder of Ride, Roll,
and Stroll Lancaster. Next slide.
Ride, Roll, and Stroll is a community
building and advocacy project that
promotes walking, bicycling, rolling,
and transit. Established in 2023, we
partner with a variety of organizations,
including the city of Lancaster,
nonprofits, and the small business
community to engage residents, industry
leaders, and elected officials. We
believe that our community and
environment is healthier and more
connected when people feel safe to walk,
bike, and take transit. Next
slide. Since 2023, we've helped the city
of Lancaster achieve bronze level
bicycle friendly community status and
engaged about 2,000 residents with bike
and transit education and advocacy.
We've curated spaces for collaboration
that have sparked current projects like
a bike bus, which is another way of
saying a familyfriendly group bike ride
to get somewhere to the Longs Park
summer
concerts. Other current projects include
letterw writing events for state
legislation to support safer bicycling
and city cycling workshops to promote
practical biking and greater freedom
greater freedom of movement in our city.
This month, we launched a free
consulting initiative to help people
address their barriers to adopting
car-free transportation methods. Next
Saturday, May 17, we'll be hosting our
second annual active transportation
summit at Bright Side Opportunity
Center. Next slide.
One of our key partners is the Lancaster
Bikes Coalition, which was established
around 2014 and has historically focused
on providing quality bike parking and
organizing annual bike counts to measure
the use and effectiveness of our city's
bike infrastructure.
The coalition currently is working to
promote municipal and business
engagement with bicycle friendly America
programs as well as bike education
programs for elementary school students
in the school district of Lancaster.
Next
slide. On behalf of Ride, Roll and
Stroll Lancaster, the Lancaster Bikes
Coalition, and our community partners,
we invite you to support our work making
Lancaster a safer place for all who use
our streets.
Get involved by attending bike month
events, including our ride, roll, and
stroll active transportation summit this
Saturday. You can also join the
Lancaster Bikes Coalition for bimonthly
virtual meetings and volunteer
opportunities. Next
slide. So, thank you councilors and
Mayor Sarra for your time and for your
support of vision zero policies that
support safe and joyful biking in
Lancaster. and please reach out if you
have any
questions. Thank you very
[Applause]
much. We have a motion and a second on
the resolution recognizing National Bike
Month. Any council comments on the
resolution from the public?
Good evening.
Good evening, counselors, mayor, public.
Thank you for uh taking the time to
recognize bike month. And could you
please begin with your name and block of
residents for the record? Sure. Carl
Feldman. I live on the 600 block of
Hamilton Street. Thank you for
recognizing bike month. Um, and thank
you to the work that the Department of
Public Works and the leaders of the city
have done to make it uh safer and more
enjoyable to ride uh but also to walk
and take the bus in Lancaster City. Um,
as someone who does not own a car and
gets to where I need to go on my bike,
that is so very important. and
everything we do to make it safer to
cycle, makes it safer to walk, um, and
even makes it safer for people who
choose to drive because, uh, it's
dangerous to be in a car, unfortunately.
So, I know that it's not perfect. You
know, uh, not everyone can feel fully
safe and comfortable on the road, but,
uh, I think there's no doubt that
Lancaster is the most advanced city of
our size in the state when it comes to
infrastructure for bikes and
pedestrians. Thank you. Thank you very
much.
Any additional comments on the
resolution from the public?
Hear none. Mr. Harris. Mr. Mint. I. Mr.
Royer. I. Mr. Gleas. I. Miss. Craig. I.
Miss. Diaz. I. Mr. Hirs. I. President
Baker.
I. Uh, council president, if I may, I
have
a resolution to present if we want to
take a quick photo to my right.
We'll excuse ourselves to do that. Thank
you for your patience, everyone.
Our next item on the agenda, uh,
resolution number 35, number 2025, Mr.
Harris.
Yes, Madam President. A resolution of
the council of the city of Lancaster
celebrating National Public Works Week
in commemoration of the tens of
thousands of men and women in North
America and the city of Lancaster who
provide and maintain the infrastructure
and services collectively known as
public works. Motion to approve. Second.
We have a motion and a second. Council
Hirs. Thank you, Council President. Um I
know we have a lot on our agenda, but I
did want to say a quick word. Uh this
resolution recognizes that May 18th,
24th is National Public Works Week. Um
this year's theme for National Public
Works Week is people, purpose, and
presence. And I know that the city's
public works department has continued to
live that out. Um, gathering uh,
feedback from the community in numerous
avenues, whether for vision zero
initiatives, public parks improvements,
holding public forums to educate
residents on what's happening, um, like
the cso meeting last month that was held
here at city hall um, to inform folks
about what's going on with our consent
decree and the fine sewer overflows. Um,
and I'll also add that if you go to the
department's page on the city's website,
uh, there are multiple videos that
highlight what the Department of Public
Works does, how they do it, why they do
it, and you can definitely check that
out if you want to learn more. Um, but
I'm proud to support this resolution
because I know there are hundreds of
public works employees that work
tirelessly and often thanklessly uh to
make sure that our city functions,
whether it's at the water treatment
plant, on our streets, in our sewers, in
our parks, or right here at city hall. I
hope this resolution can serve as a
small token of appreciation for
everything they do. And I hope we don't
take for granted the infrastructure we
have and the people and the workers that
make it happen.
Thank you very much, Councelor Hirsch.
Um, council comments on the
resolution. I will also echo your
sentiment, councelor Hirsch. Um, the
Department of Public Works uh is often
unsung for the work that they do. Um,
and uh, honestly, things are going
really well. If many city residents
don't see them, uh, at work, uh, that
means that things are going great. Um,
but we appreciate their efforts and uh
their um their mission is to be
dedicated to your quality of life. Is
that correct? Director Campbell is
nodding. Um, and I always appreciate
that reminder when I see that uh on
their vehicles and and in the
department. Um, it is true. So, thank
you to all of them. Any comments from
the public on the resolution?
Good evening. Good evening, Tony Dastro
at 700 block New Holland Avenue. I also
want to thank you uh as someone who
wears H high viz during the day and
sometimes is on the road marking out
utilities, sometimes in storm
structures, inspecting them, checking
out signs, things of that nature. Uh it
is nice to see public works recognized
and appreciated. Uh especially because I
know councelor Craig and I have had this
conversation like what is public works?
Like it it's such a broad thing that for
so many communities can mean different
things. Like for us, I'm grateful to
live in a community that owns its water
infrastructure. I'm grateful to live in
a community that actually adds bike
infrastructure. Like we do good work in
Lancaster. Uh and I'm grateful to live
in a community that values those
long-term investments and continues to
build on them. Uh because ultimately, if
it wasn't for public works, there would
be private works that are only
interested in taking the equity away
from our residents out of their pockets.
out of their homes and so on and so
forth. So, thank you for the resolution
and that's what I got. Thank you. Any
additional comments from the public on
the resolution?
Hear none. Mr. Harris, Mr. Med. I. Mr.
Roy, I. Mr. Glee, I. Miss Craig, I. Miss
Diaz, I. Mr. Hersh, I pres.
Thank
you. Right. Last item under this part of
the agenda is resolution number 38 2025.
Mr. Harris, a resolution of the council
of the city of Lancaster calling on the
legis legislature of the commonwealth of
Pennsylvania to raise the state
controlled minimum wage and to grant to
Pennsylvania municipalities the power to
make future wage control adjustments.
Motion to approve. Second. Have a motion
and a second. This is introduced by
councelor. Uh thank you, council
president. Uh in lie of reading the
resolution this evening, I just wanted
to take a moment to thank the members of
the community and other elected
officials uh from across the state,
including Governor Shapiro uh in joining
this campaign to call uh for support of
House Bill 1150, which would raise the
minimum wage to $15 in the state of
Pennsylvania. When we talk about the
crisis we face nationally in
affordability, uh many times we forget
to mention that uh there are community
members who are living off of a minimum
wage of 725 currently uh here in
Lancaster and in Pennsylvania. Uh so
this uh resolution um uh calls for the
support of House Bill 1150 um to raise
the wage and also give local control um
and um yearover increases to the minimum
wage in the state of Pennsylvania. And
uh this evening we have state
representative Nikki Rivera uh to talk a
little bit more and in support of House
Bill 1150.
Good evening, Representative. Thank you
for joining us. My pleasure. I heard the
word legislation, so I thought I'd come
join you. Uh I was invited by by
Councelor Amed, and it's very nice to
see you all and to see you as well,
mayor. Uh and to be here for the public.
Uh so State Representative Nikki Rivera
for House District 96. Um and I wanted
to talk about minimum wage and let you
know what's happening at the state level
uh and where we are with with uh with
passing this legislation. And it's great
to see that there's a resolution coming
out of our our city as well for this. Uh
so if you work hard and you play by the
rules, you should be able to support
your family uh and pay your bills, but
it is impossible to do that on a 725 uh
per hour basis. Uh that's been our
minimum wage since 2009 when
Pennsylvania first established that
minimum wage. But the cost of living has
certainly increased substantially. Uh
not even a single person can support
themselves uh when it comes to rent uh
utilities uh food and saving for the
future on a 725 per hour wage. Uh so now
as uh councelor Ahmed mentioned we are
in the middle of a housing crisis. Uh
prices are going up. uh household u
expenses are going up uh as as often as
as we can, you know, every day we wake
up and that's only going to get worse
with the tariffs that are coming up. We
need to act to ensure that
Pennsylvania's workers are getting paid
a fair and living wage and I like to
call it a living wage uh because we all
need that that level. Uh after all, our
neighbors around us can afford to uh pay
their residents a higher minimum wage.
We have New Jersey, New York, Delaware,
Maryland, Ohio, and West Virginia who've
raised their wages above Pennsylvania's.
Uh so why are we so far behind? Uh well,
here's what's happening in the capital.
Uh first of all, Governor Shapiro's
proposed budget for 2526 raises the
minimum wage to $15 an hour and $9 an
hour for tipped workers. Uh with an
effective date of January 1st of the
coming year, 2026.
What can be done by our residents uh is
to call our senators and um and
encourage them to support the governor's
budget plan to increase the minimum
wage. Uh in the house, we have
Representative Ronnie Green from
Philadelphia. She's put forth bill,
House Bill 1150, uh raising the wage to
$15 per hour. And in addition to doing
that, including a cost of living
adjustment annually. So in 2027, January
1st of 2027, there would be an automatic
cost of living increase along with the
minimum wage so that we don't fall into
these 15-year lapses of increasing uh
our minimum wage for folks. Um the cost
of living adjustment to the minimum wage
would be calculated by the consumer
index uh price index of all urban
consumers. It's the CPI-U
uh and that's for Pennsylvania, New
Jersey, Delaware, and Maryland. Uh the
bill would also give municipalities the
ability to set their own minimum wage at
what they deem fit. Uh so again, call
your senators to support this bill. I'm
pretty sure the House of Representatives
are supporting this uh in it in their
entirety. Um a living minimum wage would
reduce poverty in this area. uh fewer
people would depend on state services
because they're getting paid a minimum
li uh livable wage and the commonwealth
would turn to to uh would spend less on
social services, save money for greater
stability. Um and raising the wage would
be a win for everybody. So, um I know
I'm preaching to the choir here and
you're preaching to the choir with me.
So, please contact your senators uh and
and encourage this increase in minimum
wage. And I do say that this is what's
considered the minimum wage. We know
that the livable wage right now is even
higher than $15. We've been going for
$15 for a long time. Uh so we're just
trying to get to $15 in Pennsylvania,
but we could do a lot better than that
in the near future. So thank you for
having me. Thank you.
We have a motion and a second on
resolution 38. Any council comments
from the public.
Good evening. Bird uh and street. I am
happy about the state pressing this
forward, but I want to address council
at the local level because we just
passed um earned income for people that
only making 725 an hour and we're taxing
them. So, while the state's doing their
part and they're raising the earned
income level, the wages up, we're taxing
them out at the local level. So, I want
to challenge council to look at and I
think it was proposed that people making
less than $12,000 a year would not have
to pay earned income tax. Thank you.
Thank you, Miss B.
[Applause]
Good evening. Good evening to you, too.
My name is Jose Martinez and I live at
338 Beaver Street. Can you just speak a
little closer to the microphone? My name
is Jose Martinez and I live at 338
Beaver Street. I just wanted to know how
is this $15 supposed to help people. You
have children right now, teenagers who
are making $15 an hour and still can't
afford to get anything that they need,
let alone a grown adult. These landlords
out here are now pushing rent from
anywhere
between$,300 to $1,800 a month. They
want you to make three times the amount
in order to get a house. You get your
UGI bill and it's $32 and they charge
you $46 for delivering it to your house.
The same with has the same thing with
the water. We went from paying water
every 3 to four months to every month
now. And and it's a skyrocketed price at
that too for water where we get Texas
saying that you either have to boil it
or don't drink it because the EPA says
it's
dirty. But yet nothing nothing's coming
down for us. Everything is going up. We
can't we can't live off of $15 an hour.
I don't think it's possible. I think you
have to boost it up a little bit more or
help us out in some way. just can't do
it that way. These landlords need
stipulations. They can't do what they're
doing to us. We had families, 25
families who lived on our block from the
bottom of Beaver Street to the West End.
25 different families pushed out because
they wanted this $1,800 a month because
they can get it. Now, there's people who
are here who are getting stipens, who
are getting help from the government and
assistance and all that other stuff
because they're here to chase a dream.
Meanwhile, their dream is turning us,
our city, into a nightmare for the
residents who live out here. And you're
talking about $15 an hour. That can't
fix it at all. The only people making
money are landlords. Thank you. Thank
you,
[Applause]
Sarah. I think that speaks to refa what
you mentioned about $15 being just a
start and has we've been working toward
for a long time. So, I appreciate your
continued efforts to continue the fight
even if we get to 15.
Right. You heard her.
Mr. Dasher, good evening. Good evening,
Tony Dash of 700 block of New Holland
Avenue.
Uh, I want to echo what Miss Bird said
about tax exemptions. Uh, and
furthermore, I recognize that the
council has at least verbally said that
they're interested in an exemption up to
$12,000, but it's frankly frustrating
and maybe even embarrassing that that's
as much as we can go when that was a
pre-existing power prior to home rule.
The council could have at any point
created a tax exemption for $12,000
residents and less, uh, but chose not to
year over year. Um, maybe you just
didn't know. Frankly, I didn't know that
for a while myself. Um, so I frankly I'm
saying something now because I think we
need more than $12,000 exemption. I
think that that is just too low of a
floor, especially when we talk about the
rising cost of living and how these
things change over time. We should have
an exemption that also changes over
time. We should have something that sets
a standard for our residents going
forward so they know that they're
protected uh from additional taxation
that could burden them. I could belabor
this longer and longer, but I think I've
made my point. Thank you. Thank you.
Any additional comment from the public
on the resolution
hearing? None. Mr. Harris. Mr. Med. I.
Mr. Royal. I. Mr. Glee. I. M. I. Miss
Diaz. I. Mr. Hersh. I. President B. I.
Thank you. Counselor. Um, yes, I do have
a copy of the resolution for state
representative.
Great. Thank
you. And thank you again to
Representative Rivera for being here
with us tonight. Again, uh, this is now
the conclusion of the proclamations and
honors section of the agenda. If there's
anyone who is only here for an item
there that wants to step out, please do
so. But all are welcome to stay as we
continue with the rest of our agenda.
The next item is public comment. Again,
this is reserved for the residents that
um uh registered ahead of time to
request the opportunity to address
council. Duration of comments is limited
to three minutes per speaker. Please
begin with your name and block of
residence. Uh Mr. Harris, our first
speaker for this period. Yes, Madam
President. Our first speaker this
evening is Kenneth Miller.
Is Mr. Miller here? I didn't see him
earlier. I don't believe he is. I will
check again at the end. Our next
speaker, Mr. Harris. Yes, madam. Madam
President, our next speaker is Shannon
Butler.
Good evening. Good evening, city
council.
I'm going to be reading something. Sure,
Miss Butler, if you could begin with
your name and block of residence for the
meeting record and just make sure you're
speaking right into that mic so we can
all hear you. Thank you. Gotcha. Shannon
Butler Loot, 357 Howard Avenue,
Lancaster, PA.
Lancaster City's 2023 audit found big
mistakes in their financial records like
a $6 million error in the general funds
balance, messed up cash and interest
numbers, and other milliondoll mixups
because their bookkeeping controls are
flawed. This problem also showed up in
2022 and
2021 and they haven't fully fixed it.
Finance Chair Aurora, who wants to be
mayor, hasn't been open about these
audit issues, which raises questions
about his
transparency while he's aiming to lead
the city.
Persistent errors in the city's
financial statements since
2021, noted in Mayor Dul's 2023 audit
and prior 2022 findings reveal weak
internal controls. These issues risk
misrepresenting the city's financial
health, leading to flawed budgeting,
higher taxes, and service cuts.
The urellence on auditors to correct
errors heighten fraud
risk. Why it's important? Why does it
matter? Reoccurring errors undermine
trust and accountability and managing
public funds.
This audit highlights systematic
weaknesses in Lancaster City's finance
reporting with errors totaling millions
including a $6 million fund balance
overstatement in the general fund and a
significant interf fund
misstatements. The persistence of
similar issues from 2022 to 2023
suggests ongoing challenges internal
control
implementation. If you need further
details such as the corrective action
plan or additional context from
Lancaster City's finance financial
reports, let me know and I can search
for relevant documents or updates. Thank
you. Thank you very
much.
[Applause]
Council, Council President, I just uh
want to uh let the public know that all
of our audited financial statements are
on our website and that uh council uh
and the public have been briefed
annually by Mayor Dussel and that uh
there have been no significant findings
and that our audits year overyear have
met the highest standards. I will
acknowledge a recent report in the
newspaper related to the pension fund
and an overp payment to a police
officer. I will also make clear that
that police officer has paid back the
pension fund in totality and that Fulton
Bank who manages our pension payments is
um making additional corrections to
their internal controls and is also
refunding any loss interest related to
that. But as it relates to the audits
for the city of Lancaster, those are
available online. And we have meeting
minutes directly from Mayor Dussel
sharing the findings of each of those
audit reports for every single year that
I have been mayor and the four years
that I served as finance chair on city
council. Thank you. Thank you, Mayor
Raji. Mr. Harris, our next speaker for
this period. Yes, madam president. Our
next speaker is uh Susie Hoover.
Good evening.
Um Susie Hoover, uh East King
Street. This is going to be a little
change of pace here. Um over the past
the last few months, a lot of attention
has been given to use of force by a
member of our police department. My
following opinions on use of for force
were shaped by several experiences,
notably by serving on a federal jury in
Philadelphia involving a state trooper
accused of excessive force in 2014 in
which the trooper was acquitted. I also
completed the Citizens Police Academy in
2019 and was a neighborhood coordinator
for the East King Improvement District.
Though I have brave
reservations about accounting my
experience with the juvenile bike
riders, I think it is important to do
this evening. A number of months ago, I
was walking on the zero block of North
Queen when I heard a lot of commotion
behind me. The bikers were riding on the
sidewalk and people were rushing out of
the way. I kept walking and the bikers
moved onto Queen Street. When I got to
Ule Plaza, these juvenile bikers
surrounded around me, coming closer to
me as they rode past my face. I took out
my phone and videotaped each one of them
as they passed me. Startled, the bikers
rode away. I showed the video to a
police officer and he told me he knew
each of the boys and he would speak with
them. Their actions were clearly
psychological to harass and intimidate
me. What is disconcerting, these
juveniles definitely could be my
grandchildren and possibly my greatg
grandandchildren. On October 13, 2023, I
sent a detailed account to Chief
Menddees regarding an incident at 1:26
a.m. on September 30th, 2023 involving
the Edward Gardner shooting resulting in
an accident north Lyman East King. It
was very chaotic and officer Hatfield
attempted to tie off the area as it was
now a crimes scheme. A man at the scene
refused to move. Verbal
non-compliance and filmed as he verbally
harassed officer Hatfield. Psychological
Officer Hatfield remained very
professional and calm as he continued
his work. Officer Hatfield repeatedly
assured this man that a super
supervising officer would arrive to
speak with him, responding him with,
"Yes, sir. No, sir." The man actually
turned off his phone and called Officer
Hatfield an
obscinity, passive resistance. Officer
Hatfield continue his work without
missing a beat. I not only wrote chief
chief Mandez about the incident, I also
wrote a personal note to officer
Hatfield. People have different
experiences and different viewpoints.
Though there is nothing to be gained by
being verbally combative, it is
inappropriate to use loud, forceful,
accusatory communication, particularly
during a city council meeting. Thank
you. Thank you.
Mr. Harris, are there any further uh
commenters for this period? No, there
not. There's not. Okay. Thank you. We
will now move to our next item on the
agenda, which is reports requested by
council. Tonight, we have a presentation
from the Neighborhood Leaders Academy of
JP Mask High School, class of 2025.
Director Krasco of the Department of
Neighborhood Engagement. Welcome.
Thank you. And good evening. Can you
hear me? It's okay. Thank you. Good
evening, Mayor Sarra, um, Council
President, and members of council. I'm
here this evening on behalf of Joshua F.
Beltree, um, who's not able to join us,
but has worked so hard the last six
months, um, with the students that are
here, and I know he's watching us. So,
if we can just give him a round of
applause. He's so sad that he's not
here. We miss you, Josh. And, um, it's
an honor. He did actually he has a write
up so I just want to share some of his
words. So good evening Mayor Sarra,
members of council and neighbors of
Lancaster. My name is Joshua Beltree and
I serve as the engagement specialist in
the department of neighborhood
engagement. I have the privilege of
managing engagement programs and working
with community leaders. Over the past
six months, I've had the honor of
guiding an incredible group of students
from JP Macasy um school and through the
neighborhood leadership academy. These
young people have impressed me so much
from day one. Their level of commitment,
curiosity, and care for their community
has been so inspiring to me. Together,
we explored how local government works,
how neighbors can collaborate to create
positive change, and most importantly,
how essential youth voices are in
building a stronger and more inclusive
Lancaster.
The student cohort is part of a larger
initiative that began in 2019. And since
then, we've led a total of 10
neighborhood leadership academy groups
with over 160 residents participating
across the city. And some of them are
also um represented here this evening.
The program continues to serve as a
powerful tool for education,
empowerment, and community connections.
A recent highlight was the students
involvement in the traffic garden
project during open streets this past
Saturday. They partnered with the
Department of Public Works to design a b
uh bike safety course, use chalk paint
to create the layout, and taught younger
children about stop signs, yielding, and
pedestrian safety. All through a
hands-on biking simulation that they
created. It was a proud moment that
showed what's possible when we trust
your our youth to lead and educate their
peers. What excites me the most in these
students are most are just getting
started. What excites me most is that
these students are just getting started.
They've already expressed interest in
applying for Love Your Black mini grants
to continue leading neighborhood
projects. That's the heart of this work
is connecting education and real tools
and opportunities to take action in the
community.
None of this would have been possible um
without your support city council. So
just want to thank you. Thank you for
your continued supporting building
community in the city and also want to
acknowledge a high foundation for their
contributions um which covers the full
cost of the program and related
expenses. Now I'd like to welcome some
of the students to the podium that we
have four students that want to share
some comments and reflections on their
experience.
So, if we can have the students come up.
[Applause]
Good evening. My name is Hay Tesfi and I
live on the third 300 block on Waltair
Boulevard. Good evening, Mayor Saraji,
members of city council and
distinguished guests. We are students
from John Piercell High School and proud
graduates of the Neighborhood Leadership
Academy class of
2025. Over the past six months, we've
learned about the inner workings of
Lancaster City and how we as students
can make a real difference in our
neighborhoods. Each month, we focused on
various topics. In October, we explored
the meaning and the purpose of civic
engagement and how students like us have
the power to be leaders in our
communities. In November, we visited
city hall and learned how city services
impact our daily lives. In December, we
learned and studied the Department of
Public Works, learning about clean
water, public parks, waste collection,
as well as sustainability. Throughout
this program, we learned of the
organization of city events from
planning to execution.
Good evening. My name is Jonathan
Peters. I live on the 700 block of
Marietta. Um, and the biggest experience
that we did as a part of NLA is that we
planned a pop-up traffic garden during
open streets on Saturday. And all of the
people you see here today spent
somewhere between three and six hours
there setting it up and also running an
example to the kids on how to uh conform
to road safety. Um, essentially what we
did is we designed signs, questions,
um, and the layout of the pop-up garden
for kids to bring bikes and come bike
around in the area. And throughout the
day, we would walk them around, explain
to them what the signs meant, and teach
them about road safety.
Good evening. Um, my name is Kai
Wasnoski. I'm from the 200th block of
North Pine Street. Um, and I'm going to
share some reflections um, on the
neighborhood leadership academy and what
I learned in this experience. So, the
main thing that I really got out of this
is how I learned how important local
government is and how it's really
connected to everyday life. from the
bike lanes that I ride on every day to
get to school to um the parks that I go
to to the events like open streets um
that I run. It's really the government
that's involved through experiences like
engaging um with the Department of
Public Works and the police department.
I really gained a better understanding
of how the process works inside local
government and really appreciate that. I
also really um learned through this
experience how students and community
members have a voice and can create
change and projects they want to see. In
fact,
um, going through this program taught me
that and led me to start to lead my own
project inside Macassie um, the Mac
Cassie community to build a solar
concession stand
um, mounted on a bike that can serve as
a fundraiser for um, our sports programs
and clubs as well as building community
support for solar as a whole. And I see
that the attitude of knowing you have a
difference in the community as a really
valuable thing that all students and
community members should have. And I
really appreciate Neighborhood
Leadership Academy for teaching me
this. Good evening. My name is Michelle
Quitch. I reside on the 200th block of
South Queen Street. I will also be
sharing some of the reflections that I
had through the duration of neighborhood
leaders academy. One thing that I
believe that I really learned was what
it means to be a leader. So whether that
was when we went to town hall here for
the first time or when we went to the
police department, all of these places
we were greeted with open arms, but we
were also shown a different facet of
what it means to lead the community. We
learned how there every person has a
different role. So whether that is a
police department and a police officer
on the streets or city council managing
our legislation, change happens in many
different ways. I was also shown what it
means to be a leader through those
leading our program. Whether that is our
amazing teacher, Miss Savage, who allows
this program to happen, or Josh, who
couldn't make it, who's always leading
us and showing us different things. It
was really inspirational to me to show
that we can have our own voice. And
myself, I felt that I was able to take a
stance in leadership along with all
those here today at open streets which
was mentioned where we got to lead the
younger kids through our traffic garden
and show them how the rules work. So
even if that was on the small scale, one
day when they're older or when all these
people have grown, maybe they will be on
the streets and they will be having a
safer experience biking or using the or
using the bike lanes that might be
created because of that. So, I would
also like to say a big thanks to you,
city council, and mayor Sores for
providing us the funding for this
program because it has really been
impactful in shaping what it means to be
a leader and giving us this amazing
opportunity to meet so many different
people and have so many new experiences.
So, thank you very very much. And I
would like to give the mic to Miss Mil.
Thank
you. Amazing.
and you just experienced a few minutes
of that. That's been our experience for
the last six months. And I just wanted
to give a quick shout out um to the
teachers that are here, the school
districts that have the school district
of Lancaster that's partnered with us.
The students spent half a day. So the
school district contributed, they think
they truly believe in this program and
contributed half a day in staffing to
make sure that um the the students were
immersed in local government. Um so
thank you so much and thank you for the
comments. what incredible leaders we
have. So, at this time, I'd like to
invite uh Mrs. Amy Savage um to the
podium. Mrs. Savage has been dedicated
and part of this process for the several
years, even through co she would show up
and so I'm really thankful for her. Um
and also, um new to this year, we had
two new um teachers. So, Gabriel Payton
and um John Crest as well. So, just want
to thank you um for your continued
support. So, Mrs. Savage is going to
come and join us and she's actually
going to read the names because not all
the students are here tonight. Believe
it or not, the class is bigger. So, we
just want to record the students name
into public record. So, a 100red years
from now when their kids are Googling or
whatever happens 100 years from now,
they can see that the students were part
of this um process. So, thank you so
much and thank you Mrs. Savage.
Um before I share some names this
evening, I just want to thank Millsy and
her team and especially Josh who
couldn't be here this evening. Um the
past six months have been nothing shy of
just magical. Um we've we've grown a
lot. We've learned a lot. And I'm so
proud tonight to be able to share with
you the names of our 2025 Neighborhood
Leader Academy students. Alexander
Mau, Annais
Oieo, Angelina
Carrasco, Anthiana
Manning, Aya
Ismat, Brian
Rodriguez, Benjamin
Gillespie, Camille
Doe, Celia
Keenir. As you all hear your names, you
can scoot up front there. uh Christopher
Riierro, Cindy Reyes, Diennis
Batista, Dia
Tapalia, Elizabeth
Palasios, Emily
Ventura, Francesca
Garcia, Helanis
Maldonado, Hasset
Tes, Jenny Fam, Jonathan Peters, Juliana
Maldonado, Kaiwin
Wisnowski, Kira Kosy Martin,
Cordell Booth, Kai Layman, Lily
Ferguson, Lindseay
Bizignani, Miranda Veras, Pragia
Tapalia, Rashelle Quitch, Rihanna
Morales, Vida
Rodriguez, Lucy Weaver, Xavier Payton,
and Angelene
Palomino. Congratulations to all of
them. Thank you so much. and council, if
you can please join us for a quick
photo. Thank you for your time. Thank
you. We'll take a photo with our proud
graduates.
[Applause]
Thank you for your support.
Thank you again to all of the students
and
congratulations. And I'll give everybody
just a moment. uh who is
departing. Thank you for being here
tonight. Yes, all the parents that are
here to support as well. Congratulations
to all of
you. All right, we will move on to our
next item on the agenda which which is
reports of committees of council. These
were the meetings held on May 5th, 2025.
Uh we begin with public safety
committee. Councelor Diaz. Uh the safety
committee did not meet. Thank you.
Councelor Diaz. Public works. Council
Hirs. Thank you, Council President. The
public works committee met on May 5th
and we had one agenda item, the
resolution recognizing National Public
Works Week, which has already been
presented this evening. Um and that
concludes the report of the public works
committee. Thank you. Economic
Development Committee. Councelor Med.
Thank you, Council President. The
economic development committee did not
meet. Thank you. Finance committee
councelor Royo. Thank you, council
president. The finance committee did
meet uh during the last session to
discuss resolution administration
resolution number
372025 which authorizes the donation of
339 341 Beaver Street to Saka
Development Corporation and uh that will
be uh discussed later this evening on
the agenda. That concludes my report.
Council President, thank you. Community
Planning Committee Council Craig. Thank
you, Council President. Um U planning
did meet. We had two items on the
agenda. One being resolution number
36205 amending the official sewage
facilities plan to include AM Global
Holdings project at 617 Fremont Street.
That particular item was moved to the
27th of this month. And the other item
is administration bill number four
amending the historic district ordinance
which we will come in contact again
with a little later on here in the
legislative agenda.
Thank you councelor Craig. Personnel
committee councelor clicks. Thank you
council president. The personal
committee did not meet. Thank you very
much. That will move us right into our
legislative agenda for this evening. The
first items are heritage conservation
and historic district items. Mr. Harris,
if you would please. Yes, Madam
President. Considering the following
applications and recommendations from
the Historical Commission and Historical
Architectural Review Board for
improvements to properties within the
Heritage Conservation and Historic
Districts. The first is Horseshoe
Holdings LLC owners of 739 Matter Street
rear proposed demolition of a rear
storage building facing Crystal Street.
Next is West Art Partners, owners of 800
Buchanan Avenue proposed construction of
an outdoor deck along the building's
north elevation facing Buchanan
Avenue. Those applications were
recommended for approval by historical
commission.
Next is Mark Wilson and 10-hour Daycare,
owner of 127 East Orange Street,
requests installation of a new doorway
opening on the rear wing visible from
North Cherry Street. And that
application was recommended for approval
by the historical architectural review
board.
I'll make a motion to approve
them together. We have a motion and a
second. Council Craig, it's your
intention to take them together. Is that
right? Yes, that's what I'm asking.
Councelor Med is that you're seconding
that. Okay. We have a motion and a
second to approve each of the items. Are
there any council comments on the items?
Council President, Council Hersh, uh can
we It seems Can we receive some clarity
because
uh per the letter from the HARB, it says
that there is one application that was
approved and one that was tabled until
ARB's June meeting. And I just want to
make sure that um that we have a clear
understanding of which has been approved
by which before we would vote on this.
Thank you. Good evening. Good evening.
Betsy Logan, planning bureau chief. Um I
can provide some clarification. There
were two items on the HARP committee
meeting. Um the one that is on your
agenda tonight was approved. There's
another one that was tabled for a second
time for an addition. Um, they're still
trying to get that resolved. And you're
saying that's not any of the items that
are on the agenda tonight? The one that
was tabled. Okay. I just wanted to
clarify that. It is not on the agenda.
Thank you, Councelor Hirs. Any
additional council
comments from the public?
Good evening. My name is Jose Martinez.
I live at 338 Beaver Street and um my
concern is about the lot 349 or 341
Beaver Street lot that they want to give
to Sakai. Sir, can I just for one moment
this item is not about that but there
that will appear in our agenda. Okay.
Which absolutely. Thank you.
Any additional comments for the heritage
conservation and historic district
items?
Hearing none. Mr. Harris, Mr. M. I, Mr.
Royo. I, Mr. Please. I, Mr. Craig. I,
Miss Diaz.
Mr. Hirs. I, and President Ba, I.
Next item on our legislative agenda. Uh,
we have ordinance for final ordinances
for final passage. We have
administration bill number 3, 2025. Mr.
Harris, an ordinance of the Lancaster
City Council amending chapter 32 real
property 2323 real property sale of by
adding a subp part B to allow for the
sale of property by use of realtor under
specific conditions providing for the
repeal of inconsistent ordinances
providing for the severability of the
ordinance and providing that the
ordinance shall take effect 20 days
after the date of its adoption.
Motion to approve. Second. We have a
motion and a second. Um, this is coming
through the community planning
committee. Council Craig. Thank you,
Council President. Um, as in review, the
ordinance governing the sale of the real
real property allows sales through
sealed bids or public auction. This bill
would expand that to allow
utilizing a licensed real estate broker
to the property. Council would still
authorize the appro the appointment of a
real estate broker and authorize sale of
the property. The bill does not change
mean the means in which the city
previously sold prop properties. It adds
another
option that was presented by the mayor
and I don't know if there's anything
that she may want to add to that or if
there's any other questions. Thank you,
Councelor Craig. Mayor Sashi, anything
additional to add on this one at this
time? Uh, just to uh draw council's
attention to section one, which um
ensures that by resolution, council will
authorize specific parcels of property
to be sold through a licensed real
estate broker. And as council councelor
Craig mentioned, um council would be pro
um approving the terms, conditions, and
basis upon uh which offers received by
the licensed real estate broker will be
evaluated such that uh the utilization
of the property in the future um can be
taken into consideration. provide who
has the authorization to negotiate an
offer and accept an offer uh and uh
provide for the compensation to be paid
for the real estate broker and also
require reporting uh to city council and
the public regarding the status of any
agreements. And finally to set forth the
time frame during which offers of sale
may be solicited for such property by a
licensed real estate broker. Um and so I
just wanted to clarify that the the uh
ordinance being considered ulates all of
these items. Thank you, Mayor Sarra. Uh
may I ask a question? Uh just a finer
point. Um this
bill, it's a question I have the answer
to. This bill doesn't authorize the sale
of any particular property. This is
amending our methods of sale. Is that
correct? That is correct. This is uh
generally uh about the ways in which the
city can proceed with the sale of real
property. Thank you. And a follow-up
question. As it stands today, the final
sale of the property would also be
approved by council. Does this bill
change that in any way, shape, or form?
No, it does not. Thank you. Any
additional council comments on the bill?
Council Diaz. President, how much of the
real estate agent will receive the
percentage that they will receive for
the sale? I believe that's uh to be
negoti or to be set on a case- by case
basis by council um in the setting of
the terms. Mayor Sarra, is that correct?
Correct. Thank you.
Additional council comments on the
bill. Comments from the
public street
Um, we had a lot of conversations about
this. We don't think it is a good move
for the city at this time. We will be
paying a realer. I mean, again, that's
coming out of taxpayers dollars. The
raco board already has a realer that
they use. So, I don't understand why we
would hire another realer. It doesn't
make sense. a lot of things that the uh
city has recently done. We have a it
takes away from um the raco board is
made up of residents. So, we're taking
away from residents voices and having a
say. We did that when we had a tree
ordinance that went to the public works
department. We did that when we passed
the bike lanes to the public works
instead of the traffic commission.
That's why we have these traffic
commission. This is why we have the tree
commission. And um yet those residents
that are not elected officials voices
are not heard because it's going through
a different department. There is no
reason I think the first time that we
heard this ordinance it was about um the
fire station and the reason we wanted to
do this because council had directed the
mayor to sell a fire station. Um now we
seem to be changing it just to open up
other options which is you know
something we want to talk about. I think
about the mayor when you made your state
of the union, you talked about how many
people can't afford a water bill and
what percentage of people will not be
able to afford it coming up. But we know
when people can't afford the water bill,
their houses become condemned. We know
that goes to the raco board. Now, this
would also open this up for council to
decide what realer might want to sell
their houses. I think you're opening up
a can of worms. You're not ready. You're
not sure what it's going to do. you're
hearing, but I think it's something that
if it's really needs to be considered,
it should be put in an administrative
code where council has time to think
about it and that does not need to
happen now. I understand there's other
plans and options available for station
six, which was the primary concern for
introducing this whole bill. Thank you.
Thank
you, Mayor Sarra. May I ask a clarifying
question? Um, Miss Bird uh mentioned
Rackle. So, this bill, to my
understanding, and I've read it many
times since we've started discussing
this, does not change the process for
the Rackle board. This is simply for the
sale of public property, which would not
be any property that is under the
Rackle's control. Is that correct? Yes.
Um, and I'm going to look to uh director
delves to just correct me, but
um in the past the rackle has
transferred property to the city and the
city has transferred property to Rackle
uh in certain
circumstances. Um and we are not seeking
to replace Rackle or its work um as it
relates to um bladed property uh and
moving through the certification of
blight. This is a property that was
under the opaces of Rackle and it was
transferred to the city uh because uh it
was previously owned by the community
action partnership and Rackle did not
want to deal with it any longer. Uh and
so it came back to the city. And so now
here we are. Now th this this um not
this particular property but in the past
we have had properties transition back
and forth between rale. Uh and that is
still uh a tool that can be used but for
publicly owned property. uh we don't
typically go through the blight process
which is what the redevelopment
authority is set to do and to utilize
the tools available to it through a very
rigorous process because it means rack
takes property from private owners in
conditions of blight to redevelop it.
That is not what this bill is about.
Thank you, Mayor Sarra. I appreciate
that clarification. is still that rack
does give property to the city and this
bill addressed this. My time wasn't up.
We had finished it and turned around,
but the city has that property and the
city would own that property. So, Rackco
could give the property to the city
which would make it open up to this
ordinance that you're introducing today.
Thank you, Miss
Bird. Additional comments from the
public on the bill.
Tony Dash 700 block of New Holland
Avenue. Tonight, I suspect the passage
of admin bill 3. It is a shame that this
is the first true exercising of home
rule because the taxes were anticipated.
However, it is a disrespect to all the
residents who have some concerns with
this proposed procedure. seems clear
that this was in mind but unsaid. It
feels like it should parallel to not
allow the sale of utilities without
referendum. Maybe not worthy of a
referendum for every use, but at least
worthy of a referendum for the process.
Anyway, let's briefly address some
concerns. What's different? This takes
away some of the residents ability to
engage with the sale of our equity
unless the ad hoc rules add the
opportunity. But it's still advertised,
Tony. Well, that might hold a little
more weight with me if the city hadn't
lost a case to a resident regarding
advertising in the tree ordinance. But
we elected these people. Yeah, sure we
did, but not under a home rule charter
when we did so. And this feels like a
panic to create new rules that will be
more challenging to use with a split
council or a political difference
between the mayor and council. We didn't
elect these individuals with the home
rule intention. So to me, it feels like
a temporary usurping of power for the
sake of efficiency. But frankly, I'm not
too interested in government efficiency
right now.
There was severe opposition to districts
by at least three sitting counselors,
one in favor and three others who may
have had opinions or statements but
didn't push them strongly as far as I
saw. There was a similar energy towards
pushing the ethics commission which was
considered necessary and yet there are
no ethics concerns in Boston say within
the invisible walls of this municipality
there are no ethics concerns.
Well, if there are no ethics concerns,
then this should be no problem requiring
that the realtor, who will be
compensated by the taxpayers, be vetted
by the still forming ethics commission.
Unfortunately for the public, you keep
seeming to advocate for solutions to
resolve self-created problems and play
the victim to these issues. Any
counselor with an individual thought and
the ability to make a motion could amend
this ordinance right now to allow create
that vetting requirement, which will do
two things. one take us a step further
away from the crisis of public trust we
have across our community and two will
force the city and the new ethics
commission to prioritize the work we
need to do in this transition period not
focus on the sale of a property that's
again a self-created problem this action
is occurring too quickly for comfort but
I do see some upsides unfortunately I
think this administration and members of
council have their eyes on with big
dollar signs like a cartoon as opposed
to community equity if this passes
tonight I would not be surprised if we
see not only the sale of former Station
6, but potentially the entire Sunnyside
Peninsula. However, I hope all these
remarks will encourage you to not at
least exercise these powers if you
should pass it until a new council is in
place because the income tax was meant
to balance our budgets. But a sale of a
property with urgency makes me wonder,
what's the hurry? Seems like you're
collectively a little nervous. Some of
you won't be here next year. Thank you.
[Applause]
Susie Gomez, 100 block of North
Reservoir Street. I second uh Darlene
Bird and Tony Dastra. I think that
there's a lot of takeaways in this city
and no one is concerned about who's
filling your deep pockets, which are the
taxpayers. We pay you to do a job. We we
we rely on your expert opinion because
you guys are the ones that are looking
at everything that we
cannot and what we see here is a
problem is a problem. So I want to
reiterate uh why uh Reverend Polite came
and offered uh station 6. I'm going to
hand this to Mayor Denine Sarra if she
doesn't have it already. If you do have
it, here's another comment.
So, you did mention to me several weeks
ago that you would be willing to donate
station 6 and if we would find someone
or anyone um for this matter. I mean,
real estate property, properties that
are
on our ground should be community-based.
There's no return investment when it
comes to the residents of this city, the
hardworking taxpayers that are
getting hurt behind every decision that
this council is making, every decision.
And we're tired of the lies. So, I say
that because it's very important that
you focus on uh Mr. the the polite
family who uh you know who who he's he's
labeled as an icon in city hall. They
have come a long way. The family has
come a long way. So, I'm just giving it
back to you if you want a return
investment or if you want to be so
gracious enough to look at what's in
front of you because there is a great a
great um presentation there that can
affect a large community that is in
desperate need right now. I don't think
you guys look at the blacks and browns.
I think that you look at what's like
Tony said, dollar signs. It's to fill
your deep pockets. And it's sadly to
say, I'm not saying that you haven't
done anything good for our city because
we do see the good. But we also see the
bad. The decisions that you guys are
making is not helping the next
generation in Lancaster City. There are
more outsiders coming into our city,
taking it by force.
LLC's, why? There's hardworking
taxpayers in this city. Why do I Why do
we got to keep giving up our next kid's
future home to another
LLC? You're giving up properties for a
dollar, but there's no return
investment. We're left with what?
Nothing to work two jobs so that we can
feed our
kids. It's becoming a nuisance. You're
not listening to the public. You don't
go out to community engagement, Miss
Gomez. We sad. Thank you. And it's not
all true because you do some good
things. Let me express that. But there's
a lot harm happening in this city when
you have to see continuous deaths,
continuous issues. I appreciate it's not
it's not fair. The light is not steady.
And I appreciate if you respect my time.
Thank you. Thank you.
[Applause]
To be to be fair, I test this every time
before the meeting to make sure that
it's exactly three minutes. So, um,
additional comments from the
public. All right. Um, I do have, uh,
just one thing I want to say, uh, before
a vote and, uh, we'll call in any
additional council comments. Just want
to speak to why I support this bill. Um,
couple of things that have been said
tonight. It's not because I don't
believe in transparency. In fact, I
believe that deciding uh to utilize a
realer in the rare case that the city
decides to sell public property would be
much more public than an ad in a
newspaper. That is simply what is
required uh of us right now. It's not
because I believe that this will make us
more money. Uh it's not because I
believe that we should go out and sell
public property. Um, but I I do support
it because I believe in giving
flexibility and adding efficiency to
government processes in the rare case
when the city may want to sell public
property, which I'll remind members of
council that the last time this happened
was in the previous administration. Um,
I believe we should have better options
to do so and return properties to the
tax
roles. Any additional comments before we
call the vote?
Hearing none. Mr. Harris. Yes, Madam
President. Mr. M. I. Mr. Royal. I. Mr.
Cle. I. Miss. Craig. I. Miss. Diaz.
None. Mr. Hirs. I. President Baker. I.
We. We. We. We. We. We. We. We. We. We.
We now move to our next item on the
agenda, item C, which is ordinances for
first reading. We have administration
bill number
42025. Mr. Harris an ordinance of the
Lancaster City Council amending chapter
155 historic districts of the code of
the city of Lancaster by revising the
definition of building official and
clarifying a building official's
membership on the city of Lancaster
historical architectural review board
and historical commission providing for
the appointment of a of a building
official or officials to the historical
architectural review board andor
commission by the director of the
department of community and economic
development, providing for the repeal of
inconsistent ordinances, providing for
the severability of the ordinance, and
providing that the ordinance shall take
effect in accordance with Pennsylvania
law. Thank you for reading that, Mr.
Harris. Uh, Director Del, good evening.
Thank you for joining us for this first
read. Yes. Uh, good evening, city
council. Um as a reminder on uh May 5th
we discussed uh this particular bill uh
bill number uh
04-2025 uh that was at um council
committee meeting. Uh the bill consists
of minor amendments to the historic
district ordin ordinance as you noted.
Uh the as we uh talked about uh during
the last conversation, the current
ordinance states that one member of the
historical commission and one member of
the harb must be the city building
official. The amended ordinance that's
before you tonight as a first reading.
Uh that uh amended ordinance maintains
that requirement of having a city
building official. um but it updates the
definition of the building official to
include modern professional
certification standards for our uh
building code personnel. The amendment
also creates flexibility to select other
qualified building code staff uh to
serve on the historical commission and
HARB beyond the singular uh chief
building official. You you might
remember last time uh that I mentioned
when this code was first written, we
only had one uh city uh building
official and now we actually have a few
uh certified staff who can uh fulfill
this role. Uh and lastly, the uh
amendments to the ordinance provide for
the director of community planning and
economic development to designate the
professional who serves on historical
commission and the hard. And uh that
that I think summarizes all the the main
points in the bill. If there are any
questions, I'm happy to answer those for
you. Thank you, Director Dell. Uh one
question, uh the current um the current
ordinance that that governs this
appointment of the building official.
um that um you had mentioned at our
committee meeting that the update to the
standards was actually um it was best
practice in the state or a state level
um requirement. Can you refresh me on
what that was? Certainly. uh the the
Pennsylvania Department of Labor and
Industry has a set of certifications for
building code uh officials and uh we
we've essentially set this standard at
what's referred to as certification
number 15 uh which equates to a
commercial uh building code official. Uh
there are a number of other
certifications um I'd mentioned uh for
electricity uh plumbing um residential
uh construction etc. I think there's a
total of about 20 21 of them altogether.
So in essence, this ordinance makes it
um makes the requirements to serve on
these boards more rigorous and also we
have more of those certified uh folks
employed currently. That's correct.
Thank you. Any additional council
comments for director dels? Councelor
Med. Uh thank you, President Bac, and
thank you, Director Delps. Uh my only
question is um it's great to hear that
we have multiple people who are
certified now. Um in the future if
there's only one person who's certified
um and would the director
still appoint somebody who wasn't
certified or would it still remain only
those who are certified to serve? That
that's a great question. Uh thank you.
Uh in our case right now we have uh
three people on staff who could fulfill
that role. If for some reason in the
future um we don't have anyone who has
the proper certifications uh we would
have the power then to uh select
somebody in a contractor capacity. We
actually use third third party providers
for some of our building inspections. Uh
right now when we can't um keep up with
all of the capacity I I don't foresee
that being the case in the future. We've
made it a major priority uh to certify
our building code professionals, but in
a in a very unlikely case that that
happens um we could uh designate
somebody um through uh through contract.
Thank you. And that concludes my
questions. Council President. Thank you,
Councelor M. Additional council
comments on the first read.
Comments in the p from the public on the
first read of the
bill, having Susie Hoover, um East King
Street, having uh sat on the HARB board
and following the historic commission
and the HARB, um the one thing that
would be good, John Lefever, who is no
longer in that position, uh he was on
both of those um the harb and the
historic commission. Um the one thing
that would be very good u I know you're
going to have a couple people is that
there be continuity that the one person
be on the harp so they know the whole
history. It's a it's a problem if they
don't know what has happened in the past
and that's hard to catch up on. So I
think we I'm a little surprised because
it used to come through council this
election. Um and I guess having can
council all involved on the selection so
you all know the continuity I think
would still be a little more comfortable
with that policy. Thank you. Thank you.
And I just wanted to say um I know that
uh these um these staff place these
placements have to go through
certification.
Um, my question is before going outside
to a third party, will you at least look
within the city of Lancaster for those
that do qualify for these positions to
be
appointed before you open this door just
to get a third party involved because
you're changing legislation or you're
changing the wordings or the
descriptions to fit a different
narrative, not to fit the narrative for
the taxpayers in the city of Lancaster,
for the graduates, for for the
innovators, for the next
generation. I see you guys opening a lot
of doors to outsiders here. We're not a
metropolitan area. It's a small
city and we deserve to be respected.
This is where we live. This is where we
graduate from. And this is where we pay
our tax dollar. There should be a return
investment respectfully to all
residents.
Thank
you. Are there any additional comments
on the first
street behind you, Director D? I just
want to make sure we get to the comments
in public.
Tony Destro, 700 block New Holland
Avenue. I just wanted to say uh I think
Susie Hoover is right that this person
should be on both of these boards. So I
hope in choosing any of these positions
you continue that practice because it is
important that everybody understands the
full context in that role. That's all I
have. Thank you. Thank you.
Bird Southeast Street. Um I did like the
idea that council had a say in selecting
who sits on the board and we're taking
that away again. we're taking from the
residents that uh the elected officials
that the residents voted in to make
these decisions who's sitting on these
boards. We do do too much of consulting
in the city with these third parties. Uh
way too much. I would like to see us
looking at if council really wants to
make a change, talk about the process
because people come and they sit through
these historic uh commission meetings
and it delays projects when we're
talking about affordable housing and
it's delayed and we're not talking about
any of the process to speed that up.
We're talking about who's going to sit
on the board and let's change what's
required of them. And I think if
council's really going to do something,
let's really speak about the process.
Thank you. Thank you.
Right. I'll remind everyone that this is
a first read um of this uh of this bill
and it will appear I believe Mr. Harris
if I'm correct on at our next meeting on
the 27th. Is that right? That's correct.
Thank you very much. Thank you, Director
Elves.
Our next item on the agenda uh is item
D, resolutions. We have resolution
number 37
2025. Mr. Harris, when you're ready.
a resolution of the council of the city
of Lancaster authorizing proper
officials of the city of Lancaster to
enter into a donation agreement with
Saka Development Corporation, a
Pennsylvania nonprofit housing
corporation, pursuant to which the city
will donate the property known and
designated as 339 341 Beaver Street,
Lancaster, Pennsylvania
17602, tax parcel 33459250
to Saka Development Corporation for
development into owner occupied
affordable housing in accordance with
the terms of set agreement and to take
such other and further actions as are
necessary to accomplish the purposes and
transactions contemplated by and set
forth in the donation agreement.
Motion to approve. Second. Have a motion
and a second. Um, Mayor Sarrai, anything
additional on this resolution?
Thank you, Council President. Um, just
for uh the sake of the audience who was
not many of whom are not here at the
committee meeting, I'll just briefly
recap why this is uh before city
council. Um, as you know, this property
has had a long history. It started out
to uh it was going to be a community
garden and then um the community action
partnership purchased the property um I
believe from Mr. Charles Crystal uh and
with the intention of developing it into
a park. Um it it for various reasons
that that that did not move forward and
it seemed odd for the community action
partnership to develop a park that was
going to be owned and maintained by the
city. And so then through uh a process,
it has now become the city of
Lancaster's uh property. In
202022, we were actively moving forward
with park planning and fundraising. We
had raised $25,000
uh through uh the generous support of
Representative Smith
Wedell and um and had continued to do uh
the park planning. uh by the end of 2023
we had run into uh three significant
roadblocks. Uh one is that the adjacent
property owners in the in the back uh
their properties face uh Queen Street um
uh declined uh the subdivision of
properties uh that would uh address uh
some of the the concerns with the the
fencing and uh it's it's kind of like an
L shape if you will. So that part of the
property goes behind uh several of the
houses um on Beaver between Beaver and
Prince Street. Uh there is also concerns
related to safety uh because there was
not an exit on there's only one entrance
and one exit to the park and we had
tried to work with residents on Queen
Street to provide for a means of egress
uh out onto the other side of the park.
Uh so that continued to be a stumbling
block. And then finally uh was cost. So
the the cost of the property the cost of
developing this um uh continued to
increase. Uh we had estimated at
$250,000 and it um grew to about
$600,000
um due to a variety of needs and
circumstances uh that we were not fully
aware of when we began this process. Um,
so we had some conversations with Saka
and recognizing and as you've heard
tonight the need for affordable housing
in our community, Saka is doing a number
of projects on Beaver Street. Um, there
was a a house at the corner of Andrew
and Beaver, I believe. Is that right?
Yeah, Andrew and Beaver that u the whole
back of it was gone and they have since
raised that property and are um in the
process of bringing their building
permits uh and building land development
plan to the city to construct new
housing there. They are proposing um to
do the same uh here with this property
uh potentially uh adding five units of
affordable housing. And uh the donation
agreement stipulates um what affordable
housing means um uh in terms of the
percent median income the terms and the
length in which the affordable housing
will be able to m be maintained and
because um Saka's mission is Saka
development's mission is to provide
affordable housing this was contemplated
as um a reasonable
opportunity to donate property for the
community benefit of adding affordable
units in a neighborhood in our city. Uh
and that is the background on why this
is ahead before council tonight. Thank
you very much, Mayor Sarra, for that
recap from our May 5th meeting. Council
comments on the resolution.
Council President, if I may. Council
Hersh. Um, I just want to voice my
support for this resolution primarily
because one, it is affordable housing
that is being uh, you know, contemplated
here and that they have a track record
of doing so. Um, they've done this
multiple times in the community. They've
they've gotten it done and I think
that's really important, too. So, I
support resolution 37. Thank you,
Council Hs. Additional council comments.
Council Craig, I I just wanted to make
sure that there in in the
sale there would be stipulation
for developed affordable housing rather
than something else. Yes. Uh so there is
a deed restriction that is included as
an exhibit um that uh outlines it's 15
years that it's in effect. Is that
correct? Yeah. Thank you. Thank you. So
it um and these uh affordable housing
restrictions I I would say for Saka
Development I it's 15 years but they are
are always renewed. Saka Development has
always renewed their affordable housing
stipulations uh to concur with the HUD
guidelines of the same. So that is why
properties throughout the city that are
um were developed by SAKA continue to be
affordable to this day. It is why we've
been able to support the renovation of
some of those properties like the cigar
factory apartments at Persian and South
Lime uh with ARPA dollars because they
have stayed uh affordable housing beyond
the the original 15 years.
Thank you. Any additional council
comments? If I may council Diaz, when
you're saying affordable, what are the
prices?
So, um I believe that they are
stipulated in the resolution which I'm
I have to find my notes from the last
meeting because I believe I'm having the
same problem. Mayor Mayor Sarra, I
believe in the the restrictions is
listed that if it's sold to a uh as a
primary residence, it's limited to 80%
of the Lancaster County um in median
income. If it's uh to renters, it's 60%
of the Lancaster County median income.
Thank you. That's correct.
Additional comments from
council. Comments from the public. Sir,
how you doing? My name is Jose Martinez
and I'm a resident of Beaver Street, 338
Beaver Street. And since 2008, since I
moved on here, yes, we've been
interested in that lot. It went through
a lot of hands and we tried purchase it
ourselves. But like you said, it came
with stipulations. We couldn't build. We
couldn't do anything. That 20,000 the
mayor presented me with a $20,000 check.
We gave up $5,000 in donations for that
because Miss Buzzgo and Miss Mily came
through the neighborhood pitching for
the park. We never got anything. We
can't do anything. But now you want to
give the property that you said was
contaminated with all this stuff that we
can't do anything as residents who tried
to purchase this property. But Saka Ken,
you talk about affordable housing. When
I sat with Milsy and the people from the
the housing department, they said there
is no such thing as affordable housing.
Saka's running around here buying houses
for $40,000 and selling it for $150 to
$190,000. That's not affordable. It's
affordable to who? Visitors from
outside. People who want to buy the
property so they can turn around and
rent it for $1,800 a month or $1,900 a
month. There's a house on Persing, I
mean on on Rockland Street right now,
$629. If anyone was to go into that
property through section 8, it's $2,500
a month. Why? Because they put a couple
marble tiles on the floor. We were
promised a part. I did everything that I
was supposed to through the leadership
program in bringing my community
together. I sat there. I draw them
twice. We came up with conclusions for a
part. But what do we get told? That the
EPA said the ground is contaminated. You
can't have it. I've been called a rat.
I've been called a snitch. I've worked
with Officer Greor because we had a
fluctuation of immigrants who came into
our town who don't know nothing but to
hang out and do dumb things and they
ruined it part. I called every day. I
called every day for them for officer
Greor and everyone. And what do Milie
and them tells me? Well, due to the fact
that these people are in that park and
there's so much crime now you can't. I'm
doing what you asked me to do. Protect
the
I did everything that they asked. I
still have the lock and key to that
park. I open it at dusk and I close it
at dawn so the neighborhood kids can go
in there and still play. Right now the
grass ain't even cut because there's no
budget money for the guys who take care
of the grounds to cut it. I talked to
park and recreation. Park and recreation
hasn't been paid. Hasn't had no money in
their pockets in a long time. There's
garbage spilling over. We take care of
that lot. I cut that lie with my
lawnmower, with my gas. I take care of
the street. And where's our promise?
Where's our promise of a park? Why did
you make me gather everyone together for
a park just to snatch it away from them
and tell them they can't have it, but
Saka could have it so Saka could put
money in his pocket? We got kids who are
running in the streets playing in the
streets. 325 Beaver Street has an
aggressive pedophile who lives there. I
would like the kids not to play in front
of his house.
I I would like for the kids not to play
in front of his house. We have old
adults here who comes from other
countries who can't take their grandkids
anywhere because their parents are
working to pay back the money that they
used out here. Mr. Martinez, thank you.
We've reached three minutes. I
appreciate your comments.
Good evening. Good evening, Council.
Jessica Lopez, Lancaster City. Um, and
what was your name, sir?
Um, I'm going to second his calls. Um,
let me remind y'all that, yeah, where
Saka does refurbish these houses, sell
them, we can't get no equity off those
houses. There's no real growth when
somebody moves into that house, they
have to sell it at the price in which
they bought it. It's it's a lot of
limitations for the people that move
there. There's no real growth for that
person to to develop past them living in
those properties. So where it would be,
you know, great to keep doing this same
thing, wouldn't it be more beautiful to
give it to the person that actually been
handling this situation for the last
however long? 15 years. 15 years. And we
all know what it looks like when we
drive down Beaver Street. Them kids is
everywhere. They do need a park.
It it doesn't make any sense that he's
standing here begging you for something
that he's been cleaning up and he's been
putting his time and effort in. And
that's one thing this city gets a lot is
free
labor. Like our community puts in a lot
of volunteer work, a lot of time. We
show up here Tuesday after Tuesdays,
hours after hours. Like we don't have
our own lives and we're not paying
$1,800 a month for rent while he's free
cleaning this parking lot. If you can
clean it up and it can be feasible for
Saka to take over, why wouldn't you give
it to him? If you're going to donate it
to anybody, you're giving it away
anyway. Give it to the man that's been
doing the
job. Like this got to stop. Yes, Saka is
a great organization that keeps growing
and growing and growing beyond our city.
When does the people in our city
actually grow with
Saka? Tech Central is a great program
that puts into us. We do love Saka. Saka
has grown immensely in the last few
years. Are there no other nonprofits
that need spaces and buildings and
donations and stuff like
this? There has to be other entities.
This guy's coming asking for a church.
He can't get that. But Saka keeps
getting buildings and buildings and
buildings and buildings and buildings.
So what is this this this stuck
relationship we have with Saka? and when
does it spread into the rest of the
community outside of
Saka? I think that y'all should give
this man his part. Thank you. Thank you.
Good evening. Hi, I'm Mike Rolley Jr.
I'm Lancaster all around. I grew up on
South Street. I recently been living on
Beaver Street for like the past month.
Um I came out my door this morning. It's
raining. I see this man with a push
broom sweeping the whole street. Nobody,
nobody's paying him to do this. Nobody's
asking him to do this. He's doing this
because he wants to. And like she said,
I come outside, there's kids kicking a
soccer ball in the street, playing
around. They have to move out of the way
of cars. But once again, to reiterate, I
grew up on South End, across the street
from Jackson Middle School. We got
fields, we got woods, we got the
playground. I can run around. I had an
awesome childhood growing up. All tackle
one, football, everything. These kids
don't have that. like this field here,
this lot, it could mean a lot to that
community rather than be given away for
a quote unquote development. Like the
community needs this more than they need
houses put there. And that's all I have
to say. Thank you.
Good evening, Dardine Bird 200 B. I've
been um involved with this lot for a
long time, sitting on a lot of
committees and the back and forth or who
owns it, what's going to be done. At one
time they wanted a parking lot and then
the residents came together and they
wanted to park. It is a shame that
there's nothing that the city can do
again to help the residents and the
children. And we do know affordable
housing is very important, but we also
struggle with parking. And you know, I
think you said they're going to put five
units there. Was that correct?
And what is the assessed value of these
two properties?
I I would have to check. I don't know
that off hand.
Okay. So, that would be nice if we could
find out what the assessed value of the
property is that we are uh giving away.
I do know Jose I do know Mike Rolley
from Beaver Street because they lived on
the end street and I know they're good
people and I think they know what's best
for their neighborhood. We know that
Beaver Street has been a problem uh area
for a long time and uh we know it's been
getting better since u they started
getting involved with helping the
neighborhood out going through the NLA.
Things have been changing around and at
one time South Street was the same way.
It was very bad. People didn't want to
live there. We had a bad reputation
because of the things going on until the
residents got involved and took over. So
I do think this is an opportunity for
the residents on Beaver Street to come
in and to take over their block from
things that are happening. We ask for
participation and when we get it, we
can't keep turning our back on the
residents. Thank you. Thank you, Miss
Uh thanks to Councelor Hirs. The
assessed value of that land is
$1,500. And I would also just like to
acknowledge because it's public works
week that there were um the street uh
with you know what with the neighbors we
were identified a number of priorities
uh new lighting new paving new the
street was repaved and now also although
I know it's not directly in the
neighborhood we have uh big plans for
southwest end park which is at the
opposite end of Beaver Street and uh we
look forward to bringing that park um up
to par. Thank you.
Good evening.
Good evening. Um my name is Taylor
Raymond. I live on the 500 block of St.
Joseph Street. Um and I have two
questions about this property. Uh Jose
Martinez said that um there had been an
issue with uh the ground being
contaminated. Um is that accurate? No.
Okay. There's no EPA report related to
that property being contaminated. Thank
you. Please continue your comments.
Okay. Um, so can you also clarify uh the
stipulation for the 60% uh of their of
an income? Um, so if somebody is making
$1,000 a month and is renting uh one of
the properties that will be made here,
does that mean that the rent is can be
up to $600 a month?
Just want to make sure before we answer
if you have anything further for your
time. You can define that. um Mayor
Srachi or even if director Dela is still
here can help us define the
affordability stipulations that you're
asking about um because it's based on
median incomes. It's it would be the
area median income. So I mean if it's
60%
um actually look at the
Sorry. Um, I can sort of add a little
bit more since I didn't quite understand
the first time. If the median income of
the area was $1,000 a month, would the
rent uh be could it be up to $600 a
month? That Yeah, that's a good way to
look at it. Um, I'm going to read
directly from the resolution here. Uh,
sold to an owner. So, these are the two
stipulations. number one sold to an
owner occupier whose annual family
income is at or below 80% of the
Lancaster County area median income at
time of sale or number two rented to a
tenant whose annual family income is at
or below 60% of the Lancaster County M
um area median income. Um I read that as
not to say that the rent itself is cap
but that it is uh more so for a
lowincome
individual if that makes sense. Yes.
Yeah, let's call an expert here.
Thank Thank you, Council Hers. Uh that
that was generally correct. Uh I just
wanted to try to give a little more
detail here. Unfortunately, this isn't
the the easiest answer, but for most of
our affordable housing uh programs, we
uh use definitions that are set by uh
the US Department of Housing and Urban
Development. Um HUD establishes um uh
these levels by metrostatistical area.
Um in most cities that is the metro
area. In Lancaster County in Lancaster
it is actually Lancaster County is the
metro statistical area and the um area
median income is actually varies
according to household size. So, for
example, I just had to call up uh the
table here online specifically for uh
the Lancaster uh metro statistical area.
And these all vary according to number
of people in the household. But for
example, um a fourperson household at
60% uh limit would be a
$63,000 household. A ceiling for a
fourperson
household. and and then the rent is
calculated based on that ceiling. Uh the
concept being that uh HUD is trying to
set it at a level where a household is
not uh spending over 30% of its gross
income on rent. Thank you, Director
Dolph.
Good evening. Hi, Lauren Sleser, first
block of Coral Street. I just had a
follow-up question to Mr. Delves. Um, is
it possible to I mean I understand that
this is up for a vote now, but just for
future understanding, is it possible to
make it so that it is based on census
tract instead of the median income for
the county because that's very
different.
Thank you,
Mr. Martinez. I apologize, but you have
used your three minutes for this item.
want to address what what the mayor said
and what he asked about the contaminated
ground. The mayor said, "No, when they
broke the ground in front of me, I was
there. They pulled out car parts. They
pulled out oil tanks and gas tanks from
the ground. The gentleman themselves
said the ground was contaminated." Thank
you,
Tony Dastro, 700 block of New Holland
Avenue. Um,
so just for the sake of process, I think
we I just want to acknowledge that this
transfer of property makes sense because
it's assessed at so little value, uh,
which is permitted. Uh, but I I I feel
this, man. Like when you put that sweat
equity into trying to make your
neighborhood a community, it hurts.
Like, you know, I often hear about how
we get seven different bites at the
apple here, but no one tells you that
the seeds in an apple contain arsenic,
and when you bite the whole way down to
the core, you get a tummy ache.
So, while I appreciate that we are
adding housing, or at least the plan is
to add housing,
um it seems like we could have gone
further in some of these deed
restrictions. I mean, it actually seems
like this I I looked at the property
lines briefly back there. It is wonky.
It is way wonky. Um, but you know,
planning commission recently had a
proposal. It I don't think it was in
line with this concept. That's a
different conversation, but a pocket
neighborhood where you build these
smaller units, but you still provide a
central location for community gardens
or common space.
So in addition to the restriction on uh
affordable housing, it would have been
nice to see restrictions on the type of
housing being built as well.
Uh when I see a resident get so
frustrated, somebody who is so willing
to go through all the education, all the
process, all the learning even and look,
we're never all going to agree on
subjects. We know this. I mean,
sometimes you and I are all in
agreement. other times obviously I have
something to say.
Uh but it hurts like it hurts people to
their core.
So I just look at the situation
as honestly a a tragedy for the process
of building public trust. Um I I I think
that Miss Lopez made some solid comments
about organizations. We love them. We
love the work they do, but sometimes it
doesn't feel like the whole city's
moving along with them.
Um, and man, it just I I don't know how
else to say it, but when I see someone
come up here and talk about the blood,
sweat, and tears they've been putting
into their their
neighborhood, I I feel that.
And I'm sorry to the gentleman here
tonight who's very distressed.
Thank you.
And I just want to piggy back on what
they're saying. Um to see a resident so
involved and go through the channels and
and and just prove himself to you,
mayor, and you hand a check and give him
hope and take it
back. What does that speak upon you? You
didn't do it because it wasn't
profitable. You you the city is not
spending money on this ground that is
limited in square
footage. A ground that is easily being
taken care of by the community workers.
What were going to be what what what
what expenditures are you talking about?
Make it make sense to the children to
the gentlemen back there that basically
gave blood, sweat, and tears. You took
him through a loop and then you w him
back
in. How do you do
that? I I don't
understand. You gave him hope by handing
him a check to take it
back. I will just I will say that this
was the intention was to build a park. I
also have fiduciary responsibility and I
hear from you, Miss Gomez, that I need
to be smarter and wiser in terms of how
we are spending money. We can't put
$600,000 into a park that doesn't h
doesn't meet the basic safety standards.
In return, we are getting affordable
housing, which is also something that
you demand. So, I understand that you
are frustrated. I understand that Mr.
Martinez is frustrated. He continues to
be a light on the block in terms of the
But you continue to give $600,000 of
ARPER funds to the same organizations
that promised the community that
promised the residents gazillion things
and they don't do it. Well, that's not
true. We are building affordable
housing, new units for the first time in
50 years. More of the first time in 50
years, how many affordable housings went
up on Queen Street? Multiple buildings
have gone up that you stated was
affordable housing and it's not
affordable, but it was defined as such.
Miss Gomez, they were never fined as
such and there was no public money that
went into those housing those. We have
to literally go into the city's website
to see the $37.5 million of ARPER funds
that was
misused. And it just goes on and on. It
just goes on and on. like you you even
stated another another false uh comment.
I'll get my minutes. Thank you, Miss
Gomez. I would just like to echo the
mayor's comments and I appreciate the
neighbors who have championed turning
this lot into a park. I think that
really good things happen when neighbors
work together. Uh and it's rare. It
doesn't happen a lot. Um, but I also see
that it seems that the city was
operating toward that goal as well and
in good faith. And I think that it's
extremely unfortunate that circumstances
beyond anyone's control in this
situation like trying to navigate
easements with neighbors who didn't want
them unfortunately
um not neighbors on Beaver Street but
and other uh and other issues made that
plan untenable. Um, and I support this
uh resolution because we we hear time
and time again on council the need for
affordable housing and and yes, SAKa has
done a lot of that work. Um, but it's
because they have a proven track record
to do it. Um, and we want to make sure
that we get it right this time so that
there's not another time that this comes
back because this project fell through.
Um, and I feel like this is a way to
ensure that that happens. um and is a
way to achieve a goal that we all agree
that we need. So that that's my two
cents on the resolution.
Mr. Martinez, I appreciate it, but you
have already but you're speaking about
affordable housing and I'm sorry, Mr.
Martinez, I appreciate building for
$500,000 for people who are Mr.
Martinez.
Is there any additional
Thank you, Mr. Martinez. Are there any
additional comments from the public?
Miss Jones,
Miss Jones, good evening, Mr. Martinez.
Thank you very much.
Good evening. Thank you. Good evening.
My name is Betty Jones, 200 below South
Street. Excuse me. I'm here to um just
sort of voice my opinion about what is
going on with the Beaver Street um
property that is in the process of
possibly being in the process to be
built. So, I'm just asking the um
committee, would you guys consider to
table this until the next meeting
because it seemed to be so much
controversy going on with the the
neighbors, the people completely and I I
sort of sympathize with them because if
this was going on in my neighborhood, I
probably feel I don't say probably I
know I would feel the same way.
Children's lives are very very
important.
people life period. I know we need
housing. We need I always I'm always
fighting
for homeless people but children are
very important. Some children might not
even live to become adults if they don't
have no place to play. Okay, if we have
this property, soccer is good. I
understand that they do a lot. But
children lives are very important also.
We need to have a place for them to play
or people just to a place that people
can go and maybe a park that they can go
to. That's just my opinion. I'm just
saying, you know, I'm just voicing my
opinion, but I just feel though they
need to have it. They we need to table
this until next meeting. That's my
opinion. Okay. Thank you, Miss Jones.
Any additional comments from the public?
Sir, I appreciate but you have already
um used your comment on this particular
item. Okay, I'm I'm sorry about that.
Trying to make sure everyone has equal
time. Any additional comments?
I'm sorry.
Correct.
Are you are you wishing to give comment
on this resolution?
Yes, please. Now is the time. Now's the
time. Thank you. Uh Susie Hoover, East
King. Um I just wondered when with this
building going to Saka, um and it's
using a piece of property, uh wouldn't
it have to go through planning
commission as all new building projects
have to go and maybe zoning and parking
and all those good things? That could
actually not be a good thing. that would
not be approved or recommended.
My uh assumption is that any building
project would go through the land
development and planning project land
development the whole nine yards. They
cannot move forward with land
development if they don't have the
property. And so for them to begin the
art the process of designing and
bringing a property through land
development, this is the first step,
right? And so what happens that things
don't work out?
Then what happens?
I don't know what happens if things
don't work out. What I know is that uh
that this is a complicated site for uh
development. It's um in a very tight
neighborhood like all of our
neighborhoods. I also know that Saka has
experience with infill development which
is what this um project would be and
that we have a long working relationship
with Saka um to accomplish uh their
objectives. I also say that we know that
this project, like all of the other
affordable housing, is contingent on
continued public support for public for
affordable housing and those uh those
funds are um not part of the Trump
administration's budget moving forward.
Um I do appreciate that in the
governor's proposal, he is including uh
an increase in LITC credits. We do
utilize uh public funds uh to the extent
that we get them in the city but what
money public money we get is
insufficient to meet the need and SAKa
has continued to work um to assemble the
capital stack that's necessary that
includes public financing to build homes
and put people in
them. Thank
you. Any additional comments from the
public on the resolution?
Sir, good evening. My name is Egon
Deiarte. I live on uh Dorit Street. Um
my impression of how these
policies go down is that the solutions
are found are are imposed from the top
down and that gives certain people a
complete advantage in the way that the
things operate. And so people who come
to these meetings and who have ideas
themselves but are not on in that same
position of
hierarchy, they they they can offer good
ideas, but they don't fit your top down
solutions because your top down
solutions are are are woven in between
yourselves with all your with all your
expertise. Admittedly, you have
expertise, but you're still working from
up
here pushing down. That's my opinion.
Thank you.
Any additional comment on the
resolution?
If I may, President Council Diaz, I
would love to have the opportunity to
table this and have the community come
and speak maybe from Beaver Street. Um,
and you know, with the mayor. Um,
whether it's having a meeting with
neighborhood engagement and also
possibly having Saka, you know, if they
if they're planning to build, they
should have at least some type of
sketch, something that's going to show
that they're going to be able to build
at least to present that to the
community. That's that's that's what my
proposal is.
Thank you, Council Diaz.
I want to clarify if you're making a
motion at this time. Yes, ma'am. There's
a motion on the table to table the
resolution.
I have a question first. Councilor
Craig, your question.
Have we exhausted all the
possibilities as far as safety in the
park?
to the rear of the parcel and there um
for a variety of reasons um uh the
inability to um
uh provide safe egress. So we have spent
uh you know at least 18 months trying to
work through this um uh to come to some
resolution in which we would be able to
uh implement a park uh in in that
particular spot. I will also just say
that
um you know the the conversation is uh
and I and I appreciate Councelor Diaz's
um uh motion to table. What I will say
is that overwhelmingly in the course of
our comprehensive plan in which we
talked to 14,000 people across the city,
housing was the number one priority. It
came through loud and clear. It is why
council um put $10 million into using
ARPA funds to invest in affordable
housing. It is why um we have spent more
than $ three and a half million dollars
uh last year uh and have renovated more
than two 200 properties Chris 200
properties south of King um related to
critical repair and lead um remediation.
We we know that we need housing. I
believe that council has been solidly
behind the administration in the work
that we have been doing to support
affordable housing. And I also
understand that this is a really it's a
narrow one-way street uh in between two
major thoroughares. Cullinin Park and
South uh End Park are nearby, but you
have to cross Prince Street to get
there. I get I I understand. I am trying
uh to get to a outcome that is meeting
another need in this neighborhood which
is for affordable housing.
Council president if I may. Council
Amed. Uh this just a quick question. Um
I know that it was quoted that the land
development cost to build the park would
be around 600,000. Is that current or I
mean that could also rise with increased
costs. Um so, um if the administration
has a ballpark figure of what I know
this is a very challenging piece of
land, I also understand the community
member who spoke out tonight's
frustrations, but at the end of the day,
I mean, this is going to cost hundreds
of thousands of dollars to develop and
unbudgeted costs. So, if uh the
administration could just speak to what
the current cost would be to develop the
park. I do not have a current estimate.
That estimate was from
um 20
23 is u and director Campbell shaking
his head. Yes. So 2023 that was the cost
estimate in 2023. So 600,000 in 2023.
Yes. Approximately. And when we got when
we when we hit north of
$500,000, we we had more conversation
because we have other parks that need
that investment which is coming through
bond financing uh to support other parks
in the south of the city.
Thank you. Um and that concludes my
questions. Thank you, councilors. We
have a motion on the table from
councelor Diaz. Is there a
second?
Hearing none, that motion
fails. Um, are there any additional
comments from the public on resolution
37?
Hearing none, Mr. Harris.
Mr. M. I, Mr. Royal. I Mr. Cle, Miss
Craig, I Miss Diaz. Hi, Mr. Hirs. I
and President Baker
I have reached the end of our
legislative agenda this evening. The
next item on our agenda is the second
public comment period. Again, open for
issues not on the agenda. Duration of
comments is limited to three minutes per
speaker. Please begin with your name and
block of residence for our meeting
record.
All right. Mike Rolley Jr. Um Beaver
Street.
This um next point of mine, it kind of
touches on this the whole city, the
condition of the roads. For five years,
I was a a self-employed contractor
delivery driver like FedEx and Amazon.
But um I've had thousands of dollars out
of my pocket I have to pay for front end
damage to my vehicle from the conditions
of these roads. I could think off of my
head right now. Specifically, one on the
corner of Orange and Duke Street. I
lived on Ruby Street for about the last
eight years. If I'm coming home down
Orange Street and I'm in the left lane,
without a doubt, I'mma hit that pothole
at the corner because there's no way for
me to avoid it. And it's a dunk every
time my vehicle hits it. the streets on
Second, Third, First Street, all around
Ruby Street, Coral Street, everywhere.
Every single year without fail, they're
dug up and repaved terribly. Like, if
you cut out a a big, let's say, 4 foot
by 6 foot area out of the street and you
repave it back and it's 4 in deeper than
the rest of the street around it, is
causing me It's costing me a lot of
money and I can't be the only person
dealing with this in the city. It's very
frustrating. Every time I turn around,
I'm having to put money in fixing um all
the front end components of my of my
work vehicle and on top of the higher
cost of living and everything else we
have to deal with. It's just like where
are tax dollars going and why are the
roads like this?
Thank you. All right. Thank you.
I'd love to talk to you about UGI after
this meeting. Me, too. as someone who
lives on the southwest currently.
Good evening. Good evening, Jessica
Lopez, Lancaster City. And
um I'm sad that we're handing out
plaques and patting cops on the back
that
continually violate, assault, and abuse
black and brown
children. They fail to deescalate
incident after incident and cost this
city lawsuit after lawsuit. But I really
hate that we as a community just clap at
whatever sounds good and aren't honest
enough with ourselves to admit that
there's no way that these practices are
best. We put use people in place to be
our voices and y'all really look us dead
in our eyes and lie and say that what
our police department does is the best
they can do. It's not the best they can
do. We watch the videos. They can
definitely do better. There has to be
better practices to stand here and be
like, "These practices are best as we
watch them engage conversation with
adults and then flip them around and
dump them on their heads as we watch
them engage conversations with children
that end up in physical restraints with
police officers sitting on their backs.
As we continually watch them slam women
into cars and and repeatedly do this
stuff in the black and brown community,
we cannot say that these practices are
best. You can hand them a plaque. You
can claim accreditation. We do not have
the best practices.
And to keep sitting here saying it and
not acknowledge the fact that you've
been handed a proposal that literally
outlines why our use of force policy
should not be utilized against
children but choose not to to reframe
it, choose not to acknowledge it, choose
not to re to force policy to change
that. How is this best practices?
So, I come back to this podium Tuesday
after Tuesday, two months later,
following the March 2nd incident, and
recite the collective calls to drop the
trumped Trump charges against the
juveniles from the March 2nd
incident, as we get closer to their
court dates on June 6th, to implement a
new use of force policy specifically
geared to handling our children and an
imple and an implementation of a
civilian review for that we've been
asking for and we can renegotiate the
terms of our collective bargaining
agreement to see fit that that falls
into
place. We keep saying we can't do these
things. We can do these things. Counties
around us do these things. Lancaster
keeps saying we can't, but yet again,
neighbor county, neighbor county,
neighbor county keep showing us that we
can. I was just in Harrisburg the other
day. They have a co-responder unit. I
was just in York the other week. They
have a co-responder unit. We can't have
a co-responder unit. Why? We can't
renegotiate our terms with these with
this union. Why? Why are we stuck in
this position where our residents
literally have no protection from our
police department, but we keep saying,
"Oh, it's all falls on the collective
bargaining agreement." That's an
agreement we choose to
sign. We need to admit that these aren't
best practices. that it's nice that
somebody will give us a little plaque
and sign their name and we can hang that
on the wall, but we need to do better
and our police department needs to do
better and we need to hold them more
accountable. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you,
Council President. Councelor Amed, if I
may, I need to be excused. There's an
emergency going on at my hotel that I
have to attend to. Yes. Thank you.
Apologize. That's all right. Mr. Dastra,
Tony Dashra, 700 block of New Holland
Avenue.
Um, so I want to
actually comment on some other comments.
Uh, I acknowledge the deficiencies with
the advertising process in admin bill 3,
but it's not a requirement that you only
advertise in the newspaper for the
current existing pro. Well, now there's
a new process, but you can do more than
that. So, it's a choice to not invest in
those
more modern solutions to getting the
knowledge out there. That's one. Two, uh
it's not entirely true that someone
needs to own a property to go through
salo. In fact, sometimes the sale of
property is contingent on the approval
of a land uh a subdivision and land
development plan. So, that in itself is
not the full truth. Uh the third thing I
want to say though is it's absolutely
true the community wants housing but the
problem is that we only look through
housing through a private equity lens or
our nonprofit groups. We need to invest
in the capital ourselves to build
housing. Housing should be a public
work. We need to do better.
It's insane to me that we continue down
this path that we make this argument
essentially that only private capital
can provide for our residents. We could
do better. We could sell bonds. I mean,
clearly these projects are generating
some form of revenue. We could pay our
own residents back on bonds they
purchased from the city through the
revenues generated by housing projects.
Maybe not always defined as affordable
housing, sure, but housing nonetheless,
it meets the goal. And to the point
about easements in the other property,
let's say this, let's say a project was
planned that's affordable or low income.
The city has eminent domain power for
low and affordable housing projects. So,
we could have taken easements if we
needed to. It just seems to me that I am
often accused of making mountains out of
mole hills and it's like, no, this
little city magician over here is just
getting good at identifying slight of
hand. And I'm really frustrated by the
way we comment to the public about these
things as if it's a statement of
absolute fact. There are facts in there,
but it's a misdirection and frankly it's
concerning because that's what we get
from the federal administration. Thank
you. Thank you.
Good evening.
Good
evening. My name is Leah Strickler. I'm
on the 100 block of North Charlotte
Street. Um, I am a member of Lancaster
Stands Up and I'm representing them
tonight. Um, I apologize. I was supposed
to read this um, back earlier and I
didn't. Um, but um, today the minimum
wage in Pennsylvania is
$7.25 an hour. Every state that borders
PA has a higher minimum wage. Whether
you live in Wheeling or New York City,
you have a higher guaranteed wage than
you do in Lancaster. I am very proud of
city council this evening for passing
this resolution support to support state
senator
Charleó's bill to raise the minimum wage
to $15 an hour and allow municipalities
to send set their own minimum wage.
Raising the minimum wage will impact me
and my family directly. My husband and I
bought our house two years ago in
Lancaster City. We have lived and loved
this city for over a decade and was all
it was always our dream to build a life
and family here. By raising the minimum
wage, my family will have more financial
stability. It will open up more job
opportunities for my husband and I to
work closer to home and will ensure that
our neighbors are compensated
appropriately. If we want an an economy
that works for all of us, we have to
start addressing this now,
which on how much money we have in our
pockets. Housing costs are out of
control. Groceries are becoming
prohibitively expensive and the
government is doing everything it can to
help Trump's rich friends at the expense
of the rest of us. Raising the minimum
wage is only the first step our state
government can take by to help working
people, but it is a necessary one. By
passing this resolution tonight,
Lancaster has helped to bring each
Pennsylvania closer to earning a living
wage. Thank you. Thank you.
Starting Bird and Street. You talking
about affordable housing. I want to
know, we have four council members that
are looking for a reelection. Are you
Have you looked into rent control? What
have you found out about it? Is there
good things about it? Is there bad
things about it? We You have seven
months yet. We shouldn't have to wait
till January to find out what you're
going to do about it. So, I want to know
if council would look into rent control.
What does that mean? Is it good? Is it
bad? I'm not standing up here supporting
it. I'm standing up here asking you to
do your job, not to wait till the next
election. You say affordable housing,
but there's steps that you can take now
to really address affordable housing if
you want to. One of them is the process
that we use to even build houses. You
know, we we don't even look at that and
we need to look at that because it takes
too long to go through the process to
build houses. It shouldn't take that
long. And if we're not willing to look
at that, we can't just say, "Well,
here's a free lot over here. Oh, well,
you can put affordable housing. One
thing we keep saying is all about
neighborhoods, and neighborhoods matter.
But I come to city council and I see
neighborhoods get up here and speak over
and over again about what's best for
them. And I see this council turn their
face and vote totally against them
because they say they're doing what's
best for the city. Well, what's best for
the city is the residents. And it's time
that you represent the residents and
start really talking about what else can
you do besides what's being presented to
you as a solution. I think residents
have solutions and I know for a fact
because South Street started in 1989 and
we continue to come to council after
mayor after mayor with no solutions how
to turn our neighborhood around. Now
we're dealing with gentrification
because the neighbors made the area so
nice and so that more people want to
live there that we're dealing with
gentrification. But to sit here and keep
crying, you want affordable housing and
this is our only solution. To sit here
and offer us a lot that 39 and 40 uh on
Beaver Street that is so awkward and say
I'm putting your affordable housings
here. I heard council say over and over
again, it's not just in the city, but
how comes all affordable housing's in
the southeast? We did all these
buildings and we say they were not um
they were p private, but we could have
required that they included some
affordable housing. So, stop coming up
here and telling us your goal is
affordable housing when you're not
taking any steps or doing anything to
change that. Now, you're going to be
sitting there, at least four of you, for
another seven months. We need to see
what you're going to do. We need you to
start taking action and doing it right
now. Thank you. Thank you.
[Applause]
Any additional comments for this
period? Okay. Um just going to get right
into it. Uh so HUD uh sold 92 properties
in the city of Lancaster to LLC's.
Um, the mayor has a brother-in-law in
the city manager who is the city manager
and has cost this city an enormous
amount of debt that we're going into
bankruptcy. Many properties are being
conveyed, transferred for a dollar. Um,
we have a long list of issues like Mr.
Aoyo. I asked you if you recused
yourself from the ARPA funds and uh they
I believe you uh one United reported
that Jamie um partners with purpose are
part of the city's arper review board
review committee and if not partners
with purpose it is you um let me
rephrase that. Okay so Jamie Royo I
asked him if he recused himself from the
arbor funds and it states that he did
not. Um he is he was involved in the
review committee. Uh five million I
believe for each solicitation being made
under the ARPER funds. The city will
establish a review committee for
individuals and it's not a relative.
It's not conflict of interest. Um and
you should have not had any decisions or
been on board on that committee when it
came to the ARPER funds. So you did lie.
Uh um and also um because that's what it
states in the city's website under the
under the uh ARPER funds resolution and
the way it's Yeah. Anyways, for each
solicitation, this is off of the website
being made under the ARPER funds. The
city will establish a review board. Did
you or did you not establish that? Can
you tell us when? Um I don't understand
why other people are involved in this
conflict of interest that we are having
in our city. Conflict of interest
conflict of interest
is as a matter of
fact not gonna Miss Gomez are you
asserting that councelor Royo worked for
partners with purpose at any point
during the ARPA process? No, they were
also No, I'm not inserting that. Okay.
So anyways, the mayor stated that uh
government audit standards in 2023 and
the general funds fund balance was
overstated $6 million due from funds
funding that was overstated by $3
million and due to other funds was
understated by $3 million and non- major
governmental funds. Fund balance was
understated by $6 million and due to
other funds was overstated by $6 million
and yeartodate activity was not properly
recorded in two of the city's cash
accounts which caused the following
understatement of cash by
405,599. the understatement of interest
income of
$1.9
million84,86 and understatement of
interest expense of $2.3
million8 2.3
million89685 material audit adjusts were
proposed by the auditors and accepted by
management in order for the financial
statements to be prepared in
accordance there are very many
inconsistencies in our audit. There are
unanswered issues, expenses, and to this
this is from your city website, Miss
Gomez, and this is I appreciate, but
we've reached past three minutes. Thank
you. Nothing to do with ARPA. Doesn't
sound like it. Are there any additional
comments for this period?
Taylor Raymond, 500 block of St. Joseph
Street. Um, I'm glad that you passed the
resolution uh in favor of House Bill
1150 uh to raise the minimum wage,
putting pressure on the state to pass
that. Um, if I understood correctly, uh,
that would also give power to uh more
local governments to uh set minimum wage
in lower in smaller districts. Is that
correct? Believe that's what
Representative Rivera had mentioned.
that was in the current version of the
House
bill. The the ability for mun
municipalities to also Yes. Yes. Okay.
Um if House Bill 1150 passes, and I hope
it does, I look forward to seeing um a
resolution from city council to raise
minimum wage in the city of Lancaster
way past $15 an hour. Um, and
additionally to raise the tipped uh the
minimum wage for tipped workers as well
because there is no way that they are
getting paid a living wage. Agree.
That's a thank
you. I hope we get that
chance. Any additional comments for this
period? Hearing none, we'll close the
second public comment period and
continue with our agenda. The next item
is the report of the mayor. Mayor
Srachi.
Thank you, Council President. Uh Mayor's
Neighborhood Month kicked off uh and all
through May and the start of June, city
departments and I will be out uh with uh
residents. Um so far we've hosted a
kickoff at Penn Medicine Park with the
stormers and had a strong presence at
Open Streets this past Saturday. Just
want to really appreciate um the
students from JP McCasky, our Department
of Public Works, Community Planning and
Economic Development, um Office of
Neighborhood Engagement, uh for their um
work on Saturday. We really appreciate
it. Uh coming up is the African-American
Cultural Alliance Fair and Parade uh
starting on May 28th and SOE's Peace in
the Streets Black Party on June the
14th. And a full schedule of events is
available on our website, and I hope to
see many of you there.
Um I I want to just um conclude tonight
with recognizing two awards uh that the
city has received uh related to the
Longs Park uh wetlands project that was
completed in
2023. Um we won the Chesapeake
Stormwater Network's Bubba Award which
uh stands for best urban BMP in the Bay
Award. BMP meaning best management
practice. The prize recognizes uh the
best storm water infrastructure projects
in the Chesapeake Bay region. It
includes a $5,000 prize which will be
used to improve educational signage and
continue water quality monitoring at the
wetlands. And we also um for the same
project received a governor's award uh
for environmental excellence. Um, these
two great uh honors recognize uh the uh
work that is happening to capture and
clean 16 million gallons of storm water
a year, reducing um our pollutants that
go into the little Konosoga Creek and
eventually in the Chesapeake Bay. This
project also added 11,000 native
plantings uh creating natural habitat
and beauty. Uh, and um, the wetlands,
pathways, and accessible boardwalk also
add to the park's recreational
offerings. So, I'm really proud of our
storm water and public works teams that
pulled off this major project at Long's
Park. Um, the special recognition always
feels good and is a testament to our
commitment to clean water and the
environment. So, congratulations, uh,
Director Campbell and your team. I also
just wanted to highlight um the good
news that Socialized Catering has opened
in Long's Park at the food stand near
the park center. I'm particularly
pleased that a local business right here
from the city who also has a stand at
market is moving into that space and is
now ready to serve customers at the
park. So, make sure you go there. Their
macaroni and cheese is really good. That
concludes my report. Thank you very
much, Mayor Sarra. The next item on on
the agenda is the report of president of
council. Um, I do not have a report this
evening, so we will move into council
comments. Are there any council comments
this evening? Could that make president
council Diaz? I just wanted to talk
about um the building which is fire
station 6. I think that's fire station
6. Anyway, um in 1923, Nelson Polite
Senior was born in Lancaster,
Pennsylvania. His father, he was Abraham
Polite, was a slave from Richland, South
Carolina. Following a discussion about
the property donation to Saka, I propose
that we donate the fire station in
memory to our late council president
Nelson Polite Senior. I hope I said the
name correct. I know I miss I missed
probably an initial there. We can have
an opportunity to honor his legacy and
transferring this property to the great
nephew of Reverend Kevin Polite who will
establish a nonprofit organization to
serve the underpersed residents and
provide youth programs which is very
well needed. especially after the
incident of yesterday of the 9year-old
or the 11 year old I don't recall the
names that were um arrested in the park.
We need to desperately in the south
south we um neighborhood um being the
fact that right behind where I live is
is Lafayette
school and I move you know I I think
that it would be really something that
he has already given us the information
that he would propose to have a cooling
station um a cold blue station and food
kitchens for those that are in in need
and also you know, working with him and
providing more youth services to avoid
any other additional catastrophes or any
type of sad situations where kids are
selling drugs or shooting shooting
themselves. So, I'm just giving you the
um you know, the opportunity to think
about this is something good that we can
do for our community.
Thank you. That's all I have.
Thank you, Council
Diaz. Any additional council comments
this evening?
Hearing none and reaching the end of our
agenda, I will hear a motion to adjurnn.
Motion to adjurnn.
Second. A motion and a second. All those
in favor? I I We're joured. Thank you.